<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Christendom; or, The nature of Christ's kingdom opened, and the chiefest difficulties in divinity cleared in order to ending the controversies among Christian philosophers, scool-men [sic], and divines of all parties.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 135 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B02147</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C3933</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R171319</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">51617708</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 51617708</idno>
            <idno type="VID">175184</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B02147)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 175184)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2719:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Christendom; or, The nature of Christ's kingdom opened, and the chiefest difficulties in divinity cleared in order to ending the controversies among Christian philosophers, scool-men [sic], and divines of all parties.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 44 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>First two leaves contain t.-p. (reverse blank) and preface.</note>
                  <note>P. 24 misnumbered '14'.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: staining with some loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the National Libray of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Theology, Doctrinal --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christianity --  Essence, genius, nature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:175184:1"/>
            <p>Chriſtendom; Or, the Nature of CHRIST's KINGDOM OPENED, And the chiefeſt Difficulties in DIVINITY CLEARED: In order to ending the Controverſies among Chriſtian PHILOSO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PHERS, SCOOL-MEN, and DIVINES of all Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for the Author, 1687.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:175184:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:175184:2"/>
            <head>The PREFACE.</head>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> THE Kingdom of Chriſt is not twofold, one as he is God the Son, and the other as he is Mediator; but it is ſimply one, as Chriſt is one, admitting of juſt conception, but no diviſion. Becauſe Chriſt is not Mediator between God and Men, ſtrictly, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween two Parties, in a worldly and human Senſe common to us and Heathens; but in a heavenly, divine, and tranſcendent Senſe, through Chriſtian Faith, which Heathens have not. The Manhood of Chriſt doth neither add to, nor diminiſh from God: But it is the Organ or Inſtrument, by which God the Son, as equal with the Father and the Holy Ghoſt, doth in the fulneſs of Time, according to his own eternal Purpoſe, purchaſe the Church with his own Blood; is the Saviour of all Men, ſpecially of thoſe that believe, and doth reign and rule over the whole intellectual World for ever, without all change in God, and without all merit in Angels and Men, antecedently, to the eternal Purpoſe of God the Father, the Son, and the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> Angels, Princes, Paſtors, and Parents are inſtrumental in the work of Redemption, but not ſo as is the Manhood of Chriſt: This is principally and ſpecially inſtrumental, as being the Manhood of him who is by nature very God. Chriſt conſidered as God, is by Nature, not by Grace, the only begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Son of God the Father: Chriſt conſidered as Man was by Grace, not by Nature, the Son of Himſelf as God equal with the Father and the Holy Ghoſt, in a ſpecial and wenderful Senſe, neither by Creation as <hi>Adam</hi> and the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, nor by Adoption as the Saints, nor by natural Generation, but by mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous Conception in the Womb of a Virgin: And yet he is but one Son of God rightly conceived, as he is but one Chriſt. Conſidered as Man, his God is our God, his Father is our Father, elect Angels and Men are his Brethren and Fellows; but ſo, that he as Man exalted at God's right Hand, in all things hath the preeminence, is anointed with the Oyl of Gladneſs above his Fellows; he is the Firſt-born among his Brethren, and of every Creature; that is, of all created Beings the moſt excellent, and next unto God in heavenly Majeſty and Glory; <hi>Col. 1.15. Rom. 8.29. Heb. 1.8, 11. Joh. 20.17.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> The Man Chriſt and the Manhood of Chriſt is God Omniſcient, Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patent, Omnipreſent, Independent, Infinite, Adorable; yet not as it is Man and Manhood, but as it is by unſearchable <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion that Perſon who is in diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent reſpects both God and Man. To adore Chriſt as Man is Idolatry; to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere Chriſt as God the Son incarnate equal with the Father and the Holy Ghoſt is Chriſtian Piety. In adoring God the Son incarnate, the Word made Fleſh, we do indeed adore the Fleſh and Manhood of Chriſt, and yet not as it
<pb facs="tcp:175184:3"/>is Fleſh and Manhood, but as it is in a wonderful Senſe that Perſon who is God the Son incarnate. As I write with a white Pen, yet not as it is white, but as it is a Pen: He that is a Husband baptizeth, yet not as he is a Husband, but as he is a Miniſter: The good God doth damn the Wicked, yet not as good to them, but ſevere, yet juſt. So we rightly adore the Fleſh and Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of Chriſt, yet not as it is Fleſh and Manhood, but as it is God the Son Incarnate. <hi>That holy Thing which ſhall be born of thee, ſhall be called the Son of God, Luk. 1.35. Heb. 1.6. Mat. 2.11. Rev. 5.9, to 14. Joh. 14.1.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4.</hi> Divine Nature, as Divine, can in no inſtant be Human: Human Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as Human, can in no inſtant be Divine. But the Divine Nature as it is in God the Son, became in a wonderful Senſe Human, <hi>The Word was made Fleſh, Joh. 1.14.</hi> All the fulneſs of the Godhead dwelleth bodily in Chriſt, <hi>Col. 2.9.</hi> And the Human Nature as it is in Chriſt, became in a wonderful ſenſe Divine, that Man who is Equal and <hi>Fellow with God, Zech. 13.7. Phil. 2.6.</hi> Therefore by St. <hi>Auguſtine, lib. de Ovib.</hi> it is called <hi>Divine Humanity, and Human Divinity.</hi> Which Saying learned <hi>Sadeel</hi> doth highly approve, <hi>De verit. Human. nat. Chriſti, c. 5. Jeſus increaſed in Wiſdom and Stature, and in Favour with God and Man, Luk. 2.52.</hi> And was made <hi>perfect through Sufferings, Heb. 2.10.</hi> Had he not ſo increaſed, be muſt always have been an Infant. And yet the Manhood of Chriſt was in no inſtant imperfect and defective. When New-born, his Manhood had all the Perfection it mas ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of in that inſtant, but not all the Perfection deſigned for it at twelve years of Age. When twelve years old, he had all the Perfection he mas ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of in that inſtant, and ſo in every Succeſſive inſtant unto the time of his Paſſion. Which being reſerved for the laſt, he did patiently undergo, and ſo by Death fulfilled and finiſhed all the Humiliation-work which God gave him to do on Earth. <hi>Joh. 17.4.</hi> and <hi>19.30.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5.</hi> All true Science is by reducing things to ſome Firſt, beyond which there is no further proceeding. Now Chriſt is the Firſt and the Laſt in Religion; <hi>Rev. 1.8, 11.</hi> All the Treaſures of Wiſdom and Knowledg are hid in him, <hi>Col. 2.3.</hi> He is the Truth, <hi>Joh. 14.6.</hi> He who holds this one Truth, doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſively hold all ſaving Truth in this one: But he who denyes and reſiſts any one Truth plain and evident to his Conſcience, hath no ſaving Truth in him. Every Errour is not Sin; but every Errour touching Religion is very Sin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, and ſo it muſt needs be againſt the Foundation of Faith and Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, either directly and immediately, or remotely and conſequentially. He that is an Heretick, doth, againſt his Conſcience, love Errour, and rely on it for Life Eternal, and ſo his Errour is his Idol: And yet the love of it doth blind his Conſcience, and extinguiſh the Light of Chriſt, ſo that he cannot ſavingly diſcern his Errour, and the Turpitude of it: he is therefore ſelf condemned.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:175184:3"/>
            <head>CHAP. I. <hi>Of Divine Predeſtination.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. WHOM God did foreknow would by his Grace and free Gift in Chriſt, ſincerely believe, them he did predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate and fore-ordain to Life Eternal: and whom he did fore-know would through themſelves be ungodly, and ſo continue, them he did predeſtinate and fore-ordain to Damnation Eternal. The Divine Fore-knowledg and Purpoſe, according to which God doth pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtinate Men to Life Eternal, is from everlaſting: but the Divine Predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, according to that Fore-knowledg and Purpoſe, is not from ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting, but in the inſtant when God creates and forms us in our Mothers Womb. Which Predeſtination lies hid, as a ſecret, in God's Boſom, until it ſhew it ſelf in Heavenly Calling and Election. And then doth God elect Men to Salvation, when he gives them Faith in Chriſt, and thereby pardons their Sin, and ſeals them with his holy Spirit, and renders them truly god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, elect, and precious in his ſight, and ſevers them from among the ungodly World, as to Life Eternal. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.2, 20. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.29, 30. <hi>Acts</hi> 13.48. <hi>Jude</hi> 4. <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.4. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.15, 16. <hi>Jer.</hi> 1.5. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.10. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.11.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Indeed we are ſaid to be choſen in Chriſt before the Foundation of the World, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.4. But that is, becauſe Election in Chriſt, is from Eternity future, and things future are as preſent to God, who <hi>calleth thoſe things which be not, as tho they were;</hi> Rom. 4.17. What is future, is as real and certain as what is preſent, yet as future, it is not in preſent being, but to come, and moſt ſurely will be. Therefore Election in Chriſt, is no otherwiſe from Eternity, than Faith is: For to be choſen in Chriſt, is to be in Chriſt; to be in Chriſt is to be a Chriſtian: A Chriſtian without Faith in Chriſt, is ſimply impoſſible. Therefore no Faith in Chriſt, no Heavenly Election. But God gives Faith to <hi>Abel</hi> and not to <hi>Cain,</hi> and thereby doth difference <hi>Abel</hi> from <hi>Cain,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.7. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.8, 9. <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.11. And <hi>Abel</hi> through the ſame Faith doth renounce and repent of all his Sins, and chuſe the way of Truth, and ſincerely covenant his Soul to God, and ſo under God, and by his Grace in Chriſt through Faith, <hi>Abel</hi> is from firſt to laſt laudably and rewardably active and inſtrumental in his own Regeneration and Perſeverance, doth ſave himſelf, and doth difference himſelf from <hi>Cain, Gal.</hi> 6.4. <hi>Acts</hi> 2.40. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.16. <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.19. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.30. <hi>Luke</hi> 10.42. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.4.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:175184:4"/>
            <p n="3">3. God worketh Regeneration ever by his Word, becauſe his Word is Truth, and there cannot be Heavenly Regeneration without Heavenly Truth, as the immortal Seed thereof: <hi>John</hi> 17.17. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.23. In the ſame inſtant, as to time, God doth of naturally unwilling, unholy, and dead in Sin, make us ſupernaturally willing, holy, and alive unto Righteouſneſs, by Omnipotent Grace in us unſearchably, neither contrary to the Intrinſick Nature of the Human Will, nor dependent on it, but above it, and ſo the Will is not deſtroyed, but fanctified and ſaved. This Omnipotent Grace in us is a Divine Effect produced by God after the Counſel of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s own Will, which is the ſame for ever, and can have no new Act; <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.11. <hi>James</hi> 1.17. There is in all the godly Divine Omnipotency, like as there is Divine Nature, and the Life of God; 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.18. <hi>I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> do all things through Chriſt which ſtrength<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>neth me,</hi> Phil. 4.13. Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potency as it is in God, is the Divine Effence ſimply independent, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth of no degrees: Omnipotency as it is in us, is the Image of God a divine Effect, ſimply dependent, and admitteth of degrees, but ſo, that he who hath the leaſt degree, cannot but be a ſincere Convert, and truly godly, and yet he is freely and willingly ſo. Regeneration is entirely Gods Gift, and entirely our Duty, and ſo we do the whole through God's Grace in Chriſt: for God cannot do our Duty, or any part of it: and we without his Heavenly Grace in Chriſt can do nothing heavenly and ſupernatural, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> is Regeneration: <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.5.</p>
            <p n="4">4. God's free Grace in Jeſus Chriſt is the Fountain-cauſe of Predeſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Election to Life eternal: but God predeſtinates no Perſon to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and he reprobates no Perſon eternally ſave for his own Ungodlineſs in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> inſtant truly repented of, and breeding the never-dying Worm. To be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly, is to be reprobate to every good Work; <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.16. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Jer.</hi> 6.30. As then God doth by his Grace of ungodly make many godly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſo he doth by the ſame Grace of reprobate make many elect, and all the Elect in Chriſt he keeps from final Apoſtacy. Chriſt conſidered as Man, is himſelf elect, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42.1. Chriſt conſidered as God the Son incarnate, equ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> in reſpect of his Godhead with the Father, and the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> is the Author of Election.</p>
            <p n="5">5. In God there is neceſſarily Self-kowledg, and Self-knowledg is bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Act and Object. Therefore no Man is the Object of God's Eternal Preſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nce and Decree. But God from Eternity doth know, love, and delight in himſelf as purpoſed in time to make <hi>Adam</hi> holy, to permit his Fall, to give him Repentance and Pardon through Faith, to give him Children<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> firſt <hi>Cain,</hi> and then <hi>Abel;</hi> to permit their being born equally in Originally Sin, and to give Repentance and Salvation to <hi>Abel,</hi> and not to <hi>Cain.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:175184:4"/>ſuppoſed, all theſe things are from Eternity future; and <hi>Abel</hi> through God's Grace will moſt ſurely be penitent and ſaved; and <hi>Cain</hi> through himſelf will moſt ſurely be ſinful, impenitent, and damned: and yet they are no Object at all of God's Eternal Preſcience and Decree. God cannot go out of himſelf for an Object to terminate his Knowledg and Will upon, becauſe he is ſimply Independent, and the ſame for ever. His Omnipotent Word or Saying, Let this and that be, is the producing of it, without all new Act, Tranſition, Motion, and Change in God; <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.3, 9, 11. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 148.5.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. II. <hi>Of Perſeverance and Certainty of Salvation.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>ADam</hi> being created in perfect Integrity might well love God, though not ſure of his Perſeverance. But unto fallen Man, in whoſe Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence reigns Guilt eternal, the holy and Sin-avenging God is not at all lovely in that condition. Fear and flee from him as his Judg he may, love and draw nigh to him as his gracious God and reconciled Father in Chriſt, he cannot, till by Sin-pandoning Grace in Chriſt through Faith, his Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence be ſet free from Guilt eternal, and in the room thereof be planted godly hope of Life eternal. Every degree of this Hope muſt needs have with it intrinſecally a degree of godly Certainty, and infallible Aſſurance of Perſeverance and Salvation, becauſe it is Hope in God, who is Truth it ſelf, and cannot lie. Therefore it is called aſſurance of Hope, an Anchor of the Soul, both ſure and ſtedfaſt; better Hope, by the which we draw nigh to God: <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.11, 19. and 7.19. In reſpect of this better Hope it is that Chriſt is ſaid to be the Mediator of a better Covenant; <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.6.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As to Life Temporal, and all things worldly and tranſitory, uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty may ſuffice, becauſe true Happineſs doth not conſiſt therein, and no Man can be ſure of living another hour. But as to Life Eternal, as good never a whit as never the better, nothing ſhort of divine and heavenly Hope thereof can ſuffice to fallen Man. Now if the perſeverance of all, in whom is divine and heavenly Hope in Chriſt, be not infallibly future, and a thing that will moſt ſurely be, in God's good time, and through his Grace in Chriſt, then there is no difference between heavenly and worldly Hope, Hope in God and Hope in Man, Faith in Chriſt and Infidelity. <hi>Adam</hi> in Innocency could have no divine Hope of his Perſeverance, but only perfect Aſſurance that God would not forſake him, if he did not firſt forſake God. There can be no divine Hope of that which is not infallibly future, and God foreſees will never be. But where is divine Hope, that is, divine evidence
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:175184:5"/>that the thing hoped for is infallibly future. Now in all regenerate Souls there is planted by God divine Hope of their Perſeverance and Salvation; therefore it will moſt ſurely be; otherwiſe God is made the Author of falſe and deceivable Hope.</p>
            <p n="3">3. God keeps his Saints in this World from final Apoſtacy by the holy fear of it, this is at once a ſure pledg and principal engine of Perſeverance: <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.40. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.27. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.20. As it is holy Fear, ſo it differs in kind from the fear of Devils and Men ungodly, in whom is fear, but no holy Fear. As it is fear of Apoſtacy, ſo it differs in kind from the State of bleſſed Saints and Angels in Heaven, in whom is perfect Fear, as Fear is the ſame with reverence and tranſcendent eſteem of God, but no fear of Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy, no poſſibility of Sin.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>David</hi> in the inſtant of his Murder and Adultery was ungodly, and in a ſtate of Damuation. The reaſon is, becauſe God's Judgment over all, is by Conſcience as his Agent, in the Breaſt of Angels and Men univerſally, and for ever. And God's Judgment muſt be ſo plain, that every Mouth may be ſtopped, and all may clearly perceive the Righteouſneſs of God. But if Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons may be in the ſame inſtant both Murderers and Adulterers, and yet Godly and in a ſtate of Salvation, then cannot every Mouth be ſtopped, nor can the Conſcience of Angels and Men univerſally acquit God. There is in the Soul of <hi>David</hi> inviſibly, ſome ſpiritual Luſt againſt the Fleſh, ſuch for kind as is in no unregenerate Man; 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.9. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.17. Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered as ſpiritual, ſo it is inviſibly active for God, and not idle in the Soul: Conſidered as Luſt, ſo it is not active, but luſteth to act, and for the preſent cannot act, by reaſon of an exceſs of contrary Luſt, which doth overwhelm it, and extinguiſh all godly Act. God's gracious purpoſe in Chriſt from everlaſting concerning <hi>David</hi> cannot fail, and therefore in time he gives him Repentance and Pardon of thoſe enormous Crimes, and ſo makes advantage thereof to his own Glory, the diſgrace of Sin, the eſteem of Holineſs, the comfort of the Penitent, and the ſilencing of the Impenitent. Thus where Sin abounded, God's Grace much more abound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and from everlaſting to everlaſting God's Mercy is on <hi>David,</hi> and all other regenerate Souls; <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.20. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.17.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Infallible Certainty as it is in God is the Divine Effence, and admits of no degrees: as it is in us it is the Image of God, a divine effect, and admitteth of degrees; but ſo, that every degree thereof is truly infallible; and Certainty not infallible, is a Contradiction, as being the ſame with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain certainty. So much holy Faith in Chriſt, ſo much holy Self-know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg, Self-perception, Self-feeling, and Self-intuition: here the ſame thing is both Act and Object. As by living we know we live, and by ſeeing
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:175184:5"/>we know we ſee, ſo we believe and know we believe; <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.69. Faith and Aſſurance, as alſo Faith and Confidence are diſtinct, yet not aſunder: they differ as Cauſe and Effect: Now Cauſe and Effect are mutually related; things related are <hi>ſimul naturâ</hi> intrinſecally together, and do mutually prove and infer each other; the effect is eminently in the Cauſe, and the Cauſe as ſuch is the meaſure of the Effect; <hi>Iſa.</hi> 32.17. <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.12. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.22. Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration is the Seal of the Spirit, by which he doth prove, evidence, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate to the Heart and Conſcience of the Man regenerate through Faith, that he is God's Child by Adoption, elect in Chriſt, and an Heir of Heaven. This is divine Evidence, and therefore he is bound to believe it with divine belief. The Holy Ghoſt, and renewed Conſcience through Faith, do undivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dedly witneſs the ſame thing, yet not in the ſame reſpects: the Holy Ghoſt doth witneſs the whole as principal and ſupream, and renewed Conſcience doth witneſs the whole as by his Grace inſtrumental and ſubordinate: <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.16, 17. &amp; 9.1. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.12, 22. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.13, 14. Doubting of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation may be in a godly Man in ſuch ſort as Unbelief may, but no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. The leaſt degree of holy Faith doth ſincerely, yet not perfectly mortify, expel, and war againſt Unbelief and carnal Doubting and Uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. III. <hi>Of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt the Mediator between God and Men.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. THE Mediatorſhip of Chriſt began immediately after <hi>Adam</hi>'s Fall: For then God the Son as purpoſed in time to be Man, and as Man to die for Sin, gave Repentance and Pardon to <hi>Adam</hi> through Faith, and ſo founded the New Covenant, of which himſelf is the Mediator, principally as he is God the Son, ſubſerviently as he is Man, according to his own eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal purpoſe. The godly before his Incarnation were ſaved by Faith in Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, as purpoſed to be Incarnate, and the Godly ſince are ſaved by Faith in the ſame Jeſus Chriſt, as already Incarnate, according to that Purpoſe. Thus Jeſus Chriſt is the ſame Yeſterday, and to Day, and for ever, without Parts and Compoſition, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.8. For if he conſiſt of Parts, then he is not ſimply impartial, and then he cannot judg the World in Righteouſneſs, he muſt needs approve Murder in <hi>David,</hi> and condemn it in <hi>Cain:</hi> Which is Blaſphemy. If he be at all compounded, then he is not ſimply Chriſt: For ſimple and compounded are Contraries, as Light and Darkneſs, Sincerity and Deceit. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.12. and 11.3. If he be not ſimply Chriſt, he is a Deceiver.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:175184:6"/>
            <p n="2">2. Chriſt conſidered as Man, died for all Men, as Men fallen in <hi>Adam</hi> equally and alike, and ſhed as much Blood, and as fincerely and effectually, for <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Judas,</hi> as for <hi>Abel</hi> and <hi>Peter,</hi> and did all that lay in him as Man, to ſave all Mankind without exception, and continueth ſo to do. For he could not be a perfectly holy Man, without bearing equal and impartial love to all Men, as Men fallen in <hi>Adam,</hi> and to all godly Men as Godly. As Man he makes no difference between one Man and another, farther then they by Holineſs or Sin ſhall difference themſelves. Chriſt conſidered as God, could not die, but he who is God manifeſt in the Fleſh, God the Son incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate died in reſpect of his Body, and purchaſed the Church with his own Blood, and obtained Faith, Repentance, Pardon of Sin, Perſeverance, and eternal Salvation for <hi>Abel, David,</hi> and the reſt of the Elect in all Ages: And temporal Grace, Mercy, Priviledg, and Salvation for <hi>Cain, Judas,</hi> and the reſt of that ſort; not with deſign that they ſhould abuſe his Grace, that ſo he might have colour againſt them, and damn them: But as unſearchably foreſeeing, that he not preventing them with his heavenly Grace, they would through themſelves be graceleſs, impenitent and periſh: And he whoſe Thoughts and Ways be far above ours, purpoſed not to prevent them. Thus he is the Saviour of all Men, ſpecially of them that believe, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.10.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Chriſt conſidered as God hath no Office, but is above Office, yet not contrary to it. Chriſt conſidered as Man hath indeed an Office, and but one. From his Conception to his Birth, thence to his Death, Burial and Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, thence to his Aſcenſion and Sitting at God's right Hand in Glory, thence to his coming to judg the World, all this is but one entire office of Chriſt as Man, admitting of juſt Conception but no Diviſion. His Office as Man is to be ſubſervient to himſelf as God in the work of Redemption, this one comprizeth all.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Chriſt as Man, obedient unto Death, is our Pattern and Example, a real Martyr, and the Prince of Martyrs, he diſcharged his own Debt and Duty, and not ours, and evangelically merited for himſelf, not for us, all that Glory and Reward which as Man he hath for ever at God's right Hand. Chriſt conſidered as God incarnate, is not our Pattern, nor a Martyr, but infinitely above us, he is our Lord and our God, our Saviour and Redeemer, our Ranſom and Atonement for Sin through Faith, our All in all, he merited nothing for himſelf but all for us. Without ſhedding of Blood is no Remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: And therefore Chriſt as Man died for Sins, yet not his own but ours, not as deſerving his Death but as deſerving our Death; and he as Man, in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to God; and out of love to us, died for us, one Man for all Men, as fallen in <hi>Adam,</hi> and ſo became a Propitiation, and Counterprize for the Sin of the whole World, yet not without Faith: For he that believeth not
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:175184:6"/>makes God a Lyar, is condemned already, and God's Wrath abideth on him, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.10. <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.18, 36. The obedience of Chriſt was not two, active and paſſive, but ſimply one as Chriſt is one. As to Eternity the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition is not between active and paſſive, but between active and idle, paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive and being at eaſe. Chriſt as Man, nailed to the Croſs, and pierced with a Spear, was inviſibly active for God and our eternal Good, and not idle: And yet in the fame inſtant he was viſibly paſſive, in great pain, and not at eaſe. His Death was indeed the moſt eminent proof of his obedience to God, and love to us: But ſtill it was obedience, and therefore pleaſing to God and truly meritorious becauſe it was ſo: For no ſuffering of Man as diſtinct from obedience can pleaſe God, and profit the Soul, and merit heavenly Reward:</p>
            <p n="5">5. Had God not ſaved fallen Man at all, he had done him no wrong, but then he had been conſcious to himſelf of going contrary to his own eternal Purpoſe. For from Eternity God the Son was purpoſed to permit the Fall of Man, to be incamate, and as Man to dye for Sin, and ſo to enter into Glory, and thus to ſave fallen Man by Chriſt through Faith, and not other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. This ſuppoſed, God could not but ſave fallen Man this only way, and yet he thus ſaved him moſt freely and willingly, and not as conſtrained and under Law to a Superior. And the true reaſon why the Incarnation doth not change and compound God, is, becauſe it is the exact fulfilling of his own eternal Purpoſe: Which Purpoſe if he had not in time fulfilled, then indeed he had been changed and compounded of Yea and Nay, and had not been himſelf, Yea, and Amen, the ſame for ever, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.17, 18, 19, 20. <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.9, 10, 11. The work of Chriſt, as Mediator, is to reconcile Sinners to God. When this is fully done, and all Sin is for ever aboliſhed; and God and Men are no longer two divided by Sin, but one in perfect Love, then ſhall the Mediatorſhip of Chriſt ceaſe and have an end, as being fully accompliſhed. As when the Wound is perfectly healed there is no further need of Plaiſters. The change is not in Chriſt, but in us, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.24, 25, 26, 27, 28.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>Of the Nature of God.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. WE cannot rightly conceive of God without diverſity and diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and we may admit of no diverſity and diſtinction repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to infinite Unity and Perfection. Unity and Diverſity are well conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent, but not Unity and Diviſion, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.4, 5, 6. God is for ever good to thoſe in Heaven, yet juſt, but not ſevere: And he is for ever ſevere
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:175184:7"/>to thoſe in Hell, yet juſt, but not good: For the oppoſition is not between Goodneſs and Juſtice, nor between Severity and Juſtice, but between Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Severity, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.22. Therefore the divine Goodneſs, as ſuch, is not the divine Severity: Nor the divine Severity, as ſuch, the divine Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. They are moſt really and not chymerically, truly and not feignedly, eternally and not temporally, divers and diſtinct; and thus all in God is not God. But then what is Goodneſs to thoſe in Heaven through God's abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant Grace in Chriſt, the ſame is Severity to thoſe in Hell through their own Sin: And what is Severity to thoſe in Hell through their own Sin, the ſame is Goodneſs to thoſe in Heaven through God's abundant Grace in Chriſt; and thus all in God is God without accident, parts, and compoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and he is truly all in all: Not as excluding the Creature and ſubordinate Cauſes, but the Creature and ſubordinate Cauſes, as ſuch, conſiſt by, and depend on God, and yet they add nothing to him, they do not make him more wiſe, holy, juſt, good, powerful, perfect, bleſſed. <hi>Of Him, through Him, and to Him are all things.</hi> He is ſimply perfect, and unto what is ſimply perfect there can be no addition. God cannot be beholden to us.</p>
            <p n="2">2. God is a pure Act, eternally active, and in no inſtant idle, and God being one, the divine Act muſt needs be one. Creation, Suſtentation, Gu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernation of Angels and Men, Incarnation, Redemption, Regeneration, Juſtification, and the like, theſe are neither immanent nor tranſlent Acts of God, but Effects produced by God after the Counſel of his own Will, which is the ſame for ever, and can have no new Act. The things produced by God are numberleſs, in them is Order, Succeſſion, Priority and Poſteriority, dependence of one thing upon another. But in God by whom they are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearchably produced there is no Number, no Order, no ſucceſſive Moments and Inſtants, nothing before and after, no dependence at all; but unſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Unity, Diverſity, Eternity, Independency, Truth, Simplicity, Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Perfection, and Excellency, above Number, Order, Time, and all that we can conceive, yet not repugnant thereto. Angels and Men are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent Beings, and not having Bleſſedneſs in themſelves, they go out of themſelves by heavenly Self-denial, and ſeek it in God, in whoſe good Will and Pleaſure they reſt and terminate, as their beginning and end, their all in all, and ſo they are happy. But God being ſimply independent, true, and Truth it ſelf, cannot deny and go out of himſelf for any thing that he hath a mind to effect. It is but his Omnipotent Word, let this or that be, and it is when and how he would have it, without all new Act, Motion Change, and Tranſition in God, unſearchably.</p>
            <p n="3">3. God is, and was, and is to come, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.4, 8. He is truly paſt, truly preſent, and truly to come, and yet the ſame God, but not in the ſame
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:175184:7"/>reſpects. God as paſt, is neither preſent nor to come: God as preſent, is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther paſt nor to come: God as to come, is neither paſt nor preſent. God is eſſentially and yet freely related to all, both Angels and Men, as their Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, Upholder, and Governour for ever: this Relation was from Eternity future, and it remains to Eternity by the free Pleaſure of God. Between God and damned Men, as Men, there is eternal Relation, as between Cauſe and Effect: Between God and damned Men, as damned, there is no Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at all, but perfect and eternal Contrariety, he is for ever bleſſed, they are for ever curſed, they do implacably hate him, and he doth implacably hate them. But he doth not hate them as they are Men: For as Men, they are eternally againſt their will, the Work and Image of God, who can in no inſtant hate his own Work and Image, as ſuch: Againſt their will God doth lord and rule over them, by Conſcience, his Agent in their Boſom, and in them the Glory of his juſt Vengeance and Severity for Sin doth eternally ſhine forth, and againſt their will they fulfil the divine Law by bearing its ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Penalty.</p>
            <p n="4">4. God, as our Creator, is the way to himſelf as our Redeemer, our Sanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifier, our Bleſſedneſs and End, our All in all. For unleſs we were by Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation Men, we could not be redeemed, holy, and bleſſed Men. Yet is God no way the Author of Sin. We muſt not deny things plain, becauſe we cannot find out to Perfection things unſearchable; and too wonderful for us, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.44. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.33. Chriſt, as Mediator, is the way to himſelf as God, our Maker and our End, our All in all. For we being by Sin alienated from God, and Enemies in our Minds by wicked Works, unleſs Chriſt as Mediator, Advocate, and Interceſſor ſhall by his Grace reconcile us to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf as God, we ſhall die in our Sins and periſh for ever. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.13. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.11. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.19. The Holy Ghoſt, as Sanctifier, is the way to himſelf as God, our Maker and our End, our All in all. For we being by Nature dead in Sin, and full of Ungodlineſs and Unrighteouſneſs, unleſs the Holy Ghoſt, as Sanctifier, ſhall quicken our Souls with Spiritual Life, and by hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Regeneration make us like to himſelf as God in Righteouſneſs and true Holineſs, we can never enter into his Kingdom. <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.3, 5.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The true God is God the Father not Incarnate, God the Son Incarnate, God the Holy Ghoſt not Incarnate, one God, bleſſed for ever, the Reward and Rewarder of all Elect Angels and Men for ever, their Bleſſedneſs and the Author of their Bleſſedneſs, their All in all: And under God the exalted Manhood of Chriſt is Sole Supream over all both Angels and Men, the Firſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born of every Creature, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.15. God, as God, is ſimply inviſible: But God, as manifeſt in the Fleſh, and the Fountain-cauſe of all Good to Elect Angels and Men for ever, is perfectly ſeen of all in Heaven Face to face, and truly by Faith, yet not perfectly of all the Saints on Earth. God cannot be
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:175184:8"/>ſeen and known ſave by his own Light, and gracious Manifeſtation of Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. Now God's firſt Diſcovery of Himſelf is in and by Creation acco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap> to his own Eternal Purpoſe in Chriſt Jeſus. Antecedently to this he is not knowable by Angels, by Men, by Chriſt Himſelf as Man. <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.9, 10, 11. <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.18. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.12. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.16.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. V. <hi>Of</hi> Adam <hi>in Innocency, and the entrance of Sin into the World.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. GOD created <hi>Adam</hi> in his own Image, truly holy, and like unto himſelf, in heavenly Rectitude: This heavenly Rectitude he loſt by his Fall, and it was renewed in him, in part, by heavenly Regeneration after his Fail, but not perfectly while on Earth. The ſtate of <hi>Adam</hi> in In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency was Supernatural and not Natural: For God created all Things and conſequently <hi>Adam</hi> by Jeſus Chriſt, according to the eternal Purpoſe which he purpoſed in Chriſt Jeſus our Lord, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.9, 10, 11. This is clea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> matter of Faith, and wholly Supernatural: For of God's eternal purpoſe in Chriſt Jeſus, the light of Nature ſaith nothing at all. God only is holy by Nature, that is, eſſentially holy, like as he only is by Nature God, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.8. <hi>Adam</hi> was holy not by Nature, but by Grace and heavenly dependence o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God. Which-Grace continued with him, 'till he diſſiking the Condition in which God made him, and affecting to be independent Lord of his own Will, choſe rather to be ruled by himſelf, than by the holy, juſt, and good Will of God. And ſo God did not neceſſitate his Fall, nor deny him Grace to ſtand, nor take his Grace from him: But <hi>Adam</hi> by wilful eating of the forbidden Fruit, did expel and put God's Grace from him, and became the Author of his own Ruine.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Adam</hi> needed heavenly Grace to keep him from inward luſting after the forbidden Fruit, but not from outward eating of it. Bare Luſt as in it ſelf is not Sin; but all Luſt in Man againſt the Spirit, and after what the holy, juſt, and good God hath forbidden, is very Sin before God, tho not before Men, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.7. In ſuch inordinate Luſt the Soul is Principal, and the Body is Inſtrumental. The Body by it ſelf cannot luſt at all, the Soul as to its natural ſubſtance is the Image of God, and in that reſpect it muſt needs be innocent. But if the Soul be deſtitute of inward heavenly Grace, it is then full of ungodly and worldly Luſts inviſibly, in reſpect whereof it is enmity againſt God, and the Image of the Devil. <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.44. <hi>Jude</hi> 18. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.11, 12. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.7.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The divine Law is holy, juſt, and good, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.12. The ſum of it is, <hi>Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God with all thy Heart, and thy Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:175184:8"/>as thy Self:</hi> or, <hi>A Conſcience void of Offance both tomard God and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Man.</hi> The divine Law conſidered outwardly, as of old, written in Tables of Stone, and now in the Bible, is man fold: But conſidered inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as written in the Heart, ſo it is only one as God is one; becauſe it conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth by Conſcience in each ones Boſom, and Conſcience in each Man can be but one. Take away Conſcience, and Man is not Man but a Brute. The nature of Conſcience is to be under God and over Man; as ſuch it is a Law to it ſelf, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.14, 15. and the great Engine by which God doth govern the whole intellectual World. <hi>Adam,</hi> while innocent, was not under the Law and Covenant of Works. For the Law of Works, as diſtinct from the Law of Faith, doth not exclude ſinful Boaſting, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.27. But there could be no ſinful boaſting in <hi>Adam</hi> while innocent. The Covenant of Works gendreth to Bondage, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.24. But Bondage was not known in the World 'till Sin brought it in. <hi>Adam</hi> in Innocency was not a Slave, but a Son, even the Son of God, <hi>Luke</hi> 3.38. And his Obedience was not ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile and from meer Fear, but it was Filial, and with perfect love to God, as his moſt good and bountiful Maker, altogether lovely to ſuch as love and be like unto him in heavenly Innocency, and never forſaking them 'till firſt they forſake him. The Law of Works conſidered as ſubſervient to Life eternal, is not the Law of Works, but the Law of Faith in the Hearts of godly Men in Chriſt Jeſus. The Law of Works conſidered as repugnant to Life eremal, is not the Law of God; but the Law of Sin and Death in the Hearts of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly Men, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.27. <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.10. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.2.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Adam</hi> began to be the Figure of Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.14. the Head of Mankind, and a publick Perſon, not 'till after his Sin, Repentance, and Pardon, when God gave him Children, and thereby made him the firſt Parent, and ſo a Head and Root to all his lineal Off-ſpring in a natural way, to his own Children immediately, to the reſt of the World remotely. For look as the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> doth by natural Generation communicate human Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to all his lineal Off-ſpring, and begetteth Sons and Daughters in his own Likeneſs, after his Image, whereby they differ in kind from Brutes: So the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> Chriſt Jeſus, doth by ſupernatural Regeneration com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate divine and heavenly Nature to all his ſpiritual Off-ſpring, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getteth Sons and Daughters like unto God in Righteouſneſs and true Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, whereby they differ in kind from the ungodly World. The whole Off-ſpring of <hi>Adam</hi> doth juſtly ſuffer temporal Puniſhment for his firſt Sin: <hi>For in Adam all die,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.22. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.12. Temporal Puniſhment is well conſiſtent with eternal Joy. But Puniſhment eternal no one can poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly ſuffer ſave for his own Sin never truly repented of.</p>
            <p n="5">5. God conſidered as Law-giver doth neither will Sin, nor permit it, but doth ſimply nill, hate, and forbid it, and doth all that in him lies to prevent
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:175184:9"/>it, and the eternal ruine of all both Angels and Men. God conſidered as above Law, yet not contrary to it, doth innocently uphold Angels and Men in natural Being while they do of their own accord ſin againſt him: And ſo he doth after a wonderful and unſearchable manner willingly permit Sin, and he wills his own Permiſſion of it, but he doth not will Sin: For all that God doth will, he doth will perfectly, and without all deceit. If God do thus will Sin, then he muſt needs love and be Author of it as truly as he is of Holineſs. Which is very Blaſphemy.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>Of Juſtification.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. JUſtification and Righteouſneſs is either Legal, or Evangelical: Legal is that in the Conſciences of the Damned. So far as when on Earth they did well, refrained from Sin, ſpake Truth, and were uſeful to human Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety; God by Conſcience, his Agent in their Boſom, will for ever juſtify and acquit them, and lay nothing to their Charge. But becauſe they were ungodly and never ſoundly repented, had in them tranſcendent Vice, held it faſt to the laſt in their Hearts, and took it with them into Eternity, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſame Conſcience in their Boſom cannot but, againſt their Will, for ever juſtify and acquit God, and filence and condemn themſelves. Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical Juſtification and Righteouſneſs, is that by Faith in the Conſciences of the Elect. God, for the ſake of Chriſt, doth by the Goſpel, through Faith, freely and fully pardon all their Sins, acquit and ſet them free from Guilt eternal, and from all Curſe and Puniſhment legally due for Sin; and then through the ſame Faith, doth regenerate and ſanctify them, and doth inwardly ſentence, pronounce, judge, and eſteem them to be what really by his Grace they are, truly penitent, perfectly pardoned, evangelically juſt, and worthy of the Kingdom of Heaven for Chriſt's ſake.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In Juſtification by Faith, God doth of unjuſt make us inwardly juſt, but not ſinleſs, ſo as was <hi>Adam</hi> before his Fall, or as the Saints now in Heaven are. But the moſt holy Man while on Earth, hath Sin in him, and ſinneth in all he doth: which Sin according to legal Juſtice deſerves Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but not according to Juſtice Evangelical: for it is ſincerely repented of, and ſo it is not imputed to us, but fully pardoned for Chriſt's ſake: The eternal Penalty is pardoned, and that being aboliſhed, all other Penalty be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes medicinal and ſanctified, and as ſanctified, it is not Penalty, but Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledg and Gain to the Soul, and as ſuch is truly eligible and deſirable by a wiſe Man: tho as it is irkſom and painful to Nature, ſo it is not deſirable, but patiently to be born.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:175184:9"/>
            <p n="3">3. Between Juſtification and forgiveneſs of Sin, there is this romarkable difference. A finleſs Perſon may be juſtified, but a ſinleſs Perſon cannot be pardoned: A ſinleſs Perſon may be falſly accuſed, and by juſt Sentence cleared and acquitted from that falſe Charge, and ſo juſtified. Thus God himſelf is juſtified: but God cannot be pardoned: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.4. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.4, <hi>Luke</hi> 7.29, 35. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. It will for ever remain true, that <hi>David</hi> once was a Sinner, a Murderer, an Adulterer: but as now he is in Heaven, he is by Grace for ever ſinleſs and impeccable, and ſo is above Pardon, and cannot need it; as the whole need not the Phyſician. Juſtified he may and ſhall be for ever, and moſt ſolemnly before all at the day of Judgment; but pardoned he cannot be. Sin once done, cannot by it ſelf be undone; but by Grace Evangelical, giving us Repentance and Pardon through Faith, it may, and really is undone and unſinned.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Righteouſneſs of God in Chriſt is, through Faith, really impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to us, and inherent in us, and it could not at all be imputed to us, were it not by Faith inherent in us. In renouncing all our own Righteouſneſs as dung and loſs, that we may have compleat and eternal Righteouſneſs, even the Righteouſneſs which is of God by Faith in Chriſt, it is manifeſt that we do not renounce our very renouncing, and our very Faith in Chriſt. In order of Nature we are firſt acquitted and ſet free from Guilt eternal through Faith: this is Goſpel-juſtification. Afterward, yet in the ſame inſtant, as to time, and through the ſame Faith we are regenerated and ſealed with the holy Spirit, we love God and do good Works: this is Sanctification; <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.13. Thus Juſtification by Faith is the riſe and ſpring of Sanctification; <hi>Articulus ſtantis &amp; cadentis Eccleſiae,</hi> they are truly diſtinct, and yet not aſunder while on Earth.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Evangelical Juſtification may be conſidered two ways, either as a Gift; or as a Reward: Conſidered as a Gift, ſo it is ſimply free, and freely given of God in Chriſt by the Goſpel, and no way merited by us, but we by Faith do humbly, penitently, fiducially, obediently, thankfully, and ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtly receive it, and it becomes ours. And thus from firſt to laſt we are juſtified by Faith without Works, according to St. <hi>Paul.</hi> Conſidered as a Reward, ſo it is beſtowed upon none but the truly penitent, obedient, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate, merciful, lovers of God and his Saints, and ſuch as by godly Sincerity, and heavenly Righteouſneſs through Grace, difference themſelves from the ungodly and impenitent World: and all ſuch do evangelically me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit Juſtification before God for Chriſt's ſake. And thus from firſt to laſt we are juſtified before God by Works, and not by Faith only, according to St. <hi>James.</hi> According to legal merit God deals with all the Devils and Damned, he renders to them according to their Deeds, exacts from them the laſt Mite, and ſhews them no Mercy. According to Evangelical Merit,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:175184:10"/>he deals with the M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>hood of Chriſt, and with all elect Angels and Men. This kind of Merit is the Image of that tranſcendent Worth and Merit which is in God; the more we have of it, we are the more like to God, and abound in loving, ſerving, and praiſing God, ſaying; Not unto us, O Lord, not unto us, but unto thy Name be all the Glory: The more we do for thee, the more we are beholden to thee; for of thine own it is that we give thee. God rewards his own Grace and Righteouſneſs in his Saints, and renders to them according to their Deeds.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>Of Satisfaction for Sin.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. LEgal Satisfaction for Sin, is that of the Devils and Damned, who ſuffer eternally of due deſert, and thereby make legal compleat Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction and Amends to God for all their own Sins, to the laſt mite. God conſidered as Lawgiver, hath no pleaſure in the death of the wiched, but that he turn from his way and live. But if he ſhall in no inſtant turn, then God, conſidered as the Righteous Judg of all the World, hath perfect plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in his eternal Damnation, as adequate legal Compenſation and Amends for his Wickedneſs in no inſtant truly turned from. Evangelical Satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for Sin is, that of all the Elect in Chriſt by Faith: they through his Grace, with godly Sorrow, unſin and undo all their Sins, give Glory to God by a face confeſſion of them with grief, hatred, and ſhame, execute holy Revenge upon themſelves, humbly beg pardon, freely forgive others, renounce all legal Merit, lay hold upon the Promiſe of Eternal Mercy in Chriſt, become new Men, ſincerely obedient to God, and his Glory in the World. Thus doing they pleaſe and ſatisfy God evangelically, and render themſelves truly worthy in a Goſpel-ſenſe of pardon of Sin, Juſtification, and Life eternal, as promiſed by God, and parchaſed by Chriſt, and prepared for them before the Foundation of the World.</p>
            <p n="2">2. God can in no inſtant pardon and ſave Perſons in their Sins without Heavenly Repentance: and he cannot but pardon and ſave all thoſe who do in any inſtant by his Grace and free Gift in Chriſt though Faith, ſincerely turn from all their Sins to God, and become new Men. And yet he faveth the Penitent, and damneth the Impenitent freely and willingly, and not againſt his Will. Like as God is neceſſarily holy, juſt, and good, yet freely ſo.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Evangelical Repentance, conſidered as evangelical, is not Puniſhment, but Priviledg, and the ſweeteſt Mercy a Sinner can poſſibly partake of, as being Rep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> unto Salvation never to be repented of, it is a divine and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:175184:10"/>thing, and the Image of God, as he is the perfect hater of all Sin, and the juſt and merciful Avenger of it by renewed Conſcience, his A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent in the Breaſt of Penitent Souls. Evangelical Repentance, conſidered as Repeatance, is proper Puniſhment, as conſiſting in penitential Remorſe, Shame, Sorrow, Contrition, Self-loathing, and a ſort of Revenge; 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.11. None of this ſhould have been, if Sin had not been: and all this is irkſom and painful to Nature, and all pain, in a large ſenſe, is proper Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment. Therefore Repentance is fitly called <hi>Poenitentia,</hi> importing pain, ſmart and penance for Sin.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Debt which we, as Men, owe to God, is ſinleſs Obedience: The Debt which we, as Sinners, owe to God, is Heavenly Repentance, and in default thereof, Eternal Damnation. This Debt Chriſt neither did, nor could pay: for neither can a ſinleſs Perſon repent, nor can he ſuffer eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally. All the Elect in Chriſt through Faith, do in their own Perſons pay the Debt of Goſpel-Repentance, and ſo evangelically puniſh them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, prevent eternall Puniſhment, ſave God the labour, and obtain perfect and free Remiſſion for Chriſt's ſake, and evangelically fulfil the Divine Law: <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.4. But the Impenitent, by holding faſt their Sins, do ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them unpardonable, and their caſe incurable. Where publick Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſſion of Sin is neceſſary by Divine Law, there no Law of Man can diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe with it. Where it is not neceſſary by divine Law, there it may not be exacted, nor Money by way of Commutation: the taking of Money in ſuch caſe is unrighteous gain.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Chriſt was made Sin and a Curſe for us, he bore our Sins in his own Body upon the Tree, and God laid upon him the Iniquities of us all: but ſo, that he was altogether ſinleſs; God could not hate him, nor be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed with him, nor repute him a Sinner, nor impute Sin to him, nor lay upon him more than Corporal and Temporal Puniſhment, in order to his own eternal Exaltation and Glory at God's Right-hand. The Pain en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured by him, did differ in kind from the Pain of damned Men in Hell, and from the Pain of guilty Perſons on Earth, and was no degree thereof. For both theſe do ſuffer deſervedly for their own Sins; but Chriſt being ſinleſs, could not deſerve to ſuffer. Indeed his Perſecuters and Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers did repute him a Sinner, and imputed grievous Sin to him, and God did unſearchably permit their Sin, but he did no way will and approve it. The Soul of Chriſt was full of ſinleſs Sorrow, and his Body was full of Pain, and yet it was all but bodily Suffering; his Body being dead, his Suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring was at an end. The Body by it ſelf cannot ſuffer at all, cannot feel Pain; the Soul of Chriſt being ſinleſs, could not ſuffer ſpiritually: but his Soul ſuffered in and by his Body, in reſpect of his Body he was crucified, and died. More than Corporal and Temporal Puniſhment needed not: for
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:175184:11"/>all the finally impenitent do, againſt their will, ſatisfy for all their own Sins legally: and all the truly penitent do, through Faith, ſatisfy God evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelically, and obtain perfect Pardon and Salvation, as purchaſed for them through the Corporal and Temporal Suffering of God the Son incarnate, crucified in reſpect of his Body.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>Of Faith.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. FAith as oppoſed to Sight, is the way to Faith as oppoſed to Deceit. As Faith is oppoſed to Sight, ſo there is no Faith in Heaven, there they ſee face to face. As Faith is oppoſed to Deceit, ſo there is no perfect Faith but in Heaven. In Men ungodly is no degree of Heavenly Faith: In all godly Men there is a degree of it, in ſome more, in ſome leſs, but ſhort of Perfection in all. God is faithful, and to be ſo, is to be full of Faith, Truth, Veracity, and Fidelity, in oppoſition to Perfidiouſneſs, Unfaithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Deceit, and Lies. Now all the bleſſed Saints and Angels are perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly like to God, as he is faithful and true, and ſo muſt needs have in them perfect Faith, Fidelity, and Truth. <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.20. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.2. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.1. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.7. <hi>Prov.</hi> 20.6. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.12.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As Faith is oppoſed to Sight, ſo through it we underſtand, diſcern, apprehend, perceive, embrace, and receive ſpiritual good things ſpiritually: through it we repent of Sin, love, obey, and pleaſe God, we receive, come to, truſt in, and rely on Chriſt, we obtain Pardon, Juſtification, and right to Life eternal, we overcome Satan and the World, and walk with God in Holineſs, and Comfort on Earth, till we come to Heaven, where Faith is turned into Viſion, and Hope into Fruition. Faith as thus oppoſed to Sight, is moſt truly, properly, and ſcripturally reckoned, counted, and imputed to us for Goſpel-righteouſneſs before God, all the while we are militant in this World.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Faith in God may be evidenced, ſhewed, declared, proved, and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually demonſtrated by heavenly Regeneration and good Works; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.4. but it cannot be defined. For what is defined is finite: but God is infinite, and infinite as ſuch, cannot be finite. Believe God we may, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine him we may not. To define is to limit, and to limit God is great Sin: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.41. He that hath holy Faith in God, knoweth better by inward feeling and Self-perception the true nature of it, than any human Definition can inform him. There cannot be a Definition of Definition. Either then Faith in God is the Standard of Definition, or Definition is the Standard of Faith in God. If the former, then Faith in God is above
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:175184:11"/>Definition, more plain than it, and is not reducible to it. If the latter, then there can be no Faith in God; becauſe he is Infinite, and, as ſuch, cannot be defined. Exact Definition conſiſteth of ſomewhat general, and ſomewhat ſpecial: but all in ſaving Faith, as ſuch, is ſpecial and peculiar to the Elect, and nothing in it common to them with the Reprobate. Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance, Juſtice, Chaſtity, Faith in the unregenerate Man, as in themſelves are proper Graces and Vertues: but as relied on for Life eternal, without heavenly Regeneration, they are no otherwiſe Graces and Vertues, than as a dead Man is a Man, or an adulterous Wife is a Wife, they are but the Corpſe of Graces and Vertues, and therefore they differ in kind from Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance, Juſtice, Chaſtity, Faith as in the regenerate Man, and are no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree thereof.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Faith is in no Faculty, but it is ſeated and rooted in the Heart, and through it we underſtand, and will ſpiritual things ſpiritually. Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding and Will in Man are truly diſtinct, but not diſtinct Faculties, they are the Image of God, in whom is unſearchable Unity and Diverſity, but no Faculties. God doth willingly underſtand, and underſtandingly will, and ſo doth Man. Every intellectual Act of Man, is the Act of the Soul, or Man, and not of this or that Faculty. Faith as oppoſed to Sight, is not an Act, but through it we act holily: It is not a Work, but through it we work Righteouſneſs: It is not Obedience, but through it we obey and pleaſe God: <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.5. &amp; 16.26.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Look what Reaſon is to the human Soul, the general Organ and Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by which it doth put forth rational and intellectual Acts, differing in kind from the manner of Brutes: that is, Faith to the regenerate Soul, the general Organ and Inſtrument by which it doth put forth holy and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural Acts, differing in kind from all the Acts of Men unregenerate, and ungodly as ſuch. Certainty of Faith is proper Certainty of Senſe, yet not of bodily Senſe common to us and Heathens; but of heavenly and ſpiritual Senſe through Chriſtian Belief, which Heathens have not. Unto true believing Souls God's Word is ſweeter than Honey, and ſharper than a two-edged Sword in their Hearts; <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.103. <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.12. <hi>What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is not of Faith, is Sin,</hi> Rom. 14.23. That is, he whoſe Heart is not purified by Faith in Chriſt, in him Sin reigns, and carnal Dubitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is Lord in his Soul; and though the thing done by him as in it ſelf be lawful, yet if he doubt whether it he lawful or not, to him it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes unlawful, through the Error of his Conſcience not purified by Faith. An erroneous Conſcience conſidered as erroneous, connot bind; for as er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous, it is not Conſcience, but the Error and Abuſe of it. But conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered as Conſcience, under God and over Man, ſo it doth truly bind to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:175184:12"/>all Duty, and againſt all Sin and Error. Whatſoever is not of Faith, is of Infidelity, and conſequently of Sin.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. IX. <hi>Of Love to God, and Self-love.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. SIncere Love is to love God, becauſe of his firſt Love to us, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.19. For this is to love him as indeed he is, our Maker, our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeemer, our Sanctifier, our Reward and Rewarder, our God and Portion for ever, our All in All, dearer to us than we are or can be to our ſelves; and to love him under any other notion, is to love an Idol and not God. Self-love, conſidered as repugnant to Life eternal, is ſelf-deſtroying Vice, and the common Character of all the ungodly; 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1, 2. Self-love, conſidered as ſubſervient to Life eternal, is, in a large and true Senſe, heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Self-denial, and the true Love of God, as good to our Souls in Chriſt Jeſus eternally: <hi>Prov.</hi> 9.12. <hi>Luke</hi> 9.23.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Vertue is truly lovely for it ſelf: but then the higheſt Vertue is to love and be like unto God; and God is not at all lovely, unleſs he be eſſentially, and yet freely the Rewarder of them that diligently ſeek him; and no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſhort of God himſelf, as enjoyed in eternal Bleſſedneſs, can content the holy ſeeking Soul. <hi>If in this Life only we have hope in Chriſt, we are of all Men moſt miſerable.</hi> To ſay, I would love God though there were no Heaven, and I would hate Sin, though there were no Hell, is in effect to ſay, I would love God though he were not at all lovely, and I would hate Sin, though it were not at all hateful and abominable: <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.6. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.19.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The chief End of Man is but one, as God is one. Subordinate Ends indeed are many, but as ſubordinate, they are not Ends, but regular means conducing to the End. The Supream End of Man is eternal Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or God himſelf as enjoyed in eternal Felicity. Eternal Salvation is not an End ſubordinate to the Glory of God; but God's Glory is his Will, as fulfilled in the eternal Salvation of all the Elect by Faith in Chriſt. God is our Salvation, and our Saviour, our Bleſſedneſs, and the Author of our Bleſſedneſs. No Man can will his own Annihilation as a means to God's Glory: for a Man as ſuch is the Image and Glory of God, and the eternal extinction of God's Glory, cannot be a means to God's Glory: for that is no means which deſtroys the End, and is repugnant to it. Indeed the damned in Hell do will and deſire their own Annihilation, but not as a means to God's Glory: for that is a holy and regular Will and Deſire; but no holy and regular Will can be in the damned. <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> could not
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:175184:12"/>without Sin, wiſh to themſelves eternal Pain, and more than barely Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral. For eternal Pain conſiſts in implacably hating and being hated of God, eternal Self-tormenting Anguiſh for Sin, and the never-dying Worm. This no Man in his right Wits can wiſh to himſelf.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Man's chief End is not to glorify God, and to enjoy him for ever. This indeed is Man's Duty, but Duty as ſuch is not the chief End, but eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Felicity, as the Reward of Duty. Chriſt as Man, when on Earth, did perfectly glorify God, and had Fruition of him in perfect Love, and yet he was not in Joy and Felicity when in his Agony, and upon the Croſs, but in the way to it, and for the Joy and Felicity ſet before him as his ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream End, he endured the Shame and Sorrow of the Croſs: <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.2. Now what is not the ſupream End in one inſtant, can in no inſtant be it, becauſe it is the ſame for ever. Thoſe in Hell do, againſt their Will, for ever glorify God, by bearing his juſt Vengeance for Sin. We glorifying God through Faith, by ſincere Obedience on Earth, God's Promiſe is to reward and crown us with eternal Bleſſedneſs in Heaven. And it is this, and this only, which is the chief End and ſupream Good of Man, as comprizing all Good in one, beyond which nothing is deſirable.</p>
            <p n="5">5. God is not loved at all unleſs he be loved incomparably. Tho he be good, better, and beſt, yet not in a way of ſtrict Compariſon, but in a tranſcendent Senſe, wherein words are to ſerve things, and not things words. Indeed ungodly Men are ſaid to love Pleaſures more than God. But the meaning thereof is not, that they love God a little, and Pleaſures more: but they love Pleaſures with all their Heart, and God but as ſubſervient. Now God as ſubſervient to Luſt and Pleaſure, is not God, but an Idol; and Idolatry is not Love, but ungodly Luſt. As Happineſs means Eaſe, Pleaſure, and freedom from Pain, Miſery, and troubleſom Want; ſo all Men naturally deſire to be happy. But as Happineſs means beholding God's Face in Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, and being ſatisfied with his Likeneſs; <hi>Pſal.</hi> 17.15. So it is wholly ſupernatural, known, and deſired of none in this World, ſave only the Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate through Faith in Chriſt. Men ungodly neglect ſo great Salvation, and ſay unto God, Depart from us; <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.3. <hi>Job</hi> 21.14. The Heaven and Happineſs deſired by them, is a ſenſual Paradiſe, and perpetual Epicuriſm: this really is not Heaven and Happineſs, but a Luſt or Idol clothed with the name of Heaven and Happineſs. The ſincere deſire of Grace as ſuch, is not the Grace deſired, but it is an infallible proof of a gracious and godly Man, as being accompanied with ſincere Performance and Endeavour, and is indeed it ſelf holy Reformance before God. There is in God delight to Love; <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.15. and in all bleſſed Saints and Angels, and there is in all true Saints on Earth ſincere deſire to love God perfectly, but no ſuch thing as love to love: this is not true Love, but adulterous Luſt. He that
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:175184:13"/>loves to love, doth not love God, but himſelf. No godly Man dare Sin: For he that dare Sin is preſumptuous, and treads Conſcience under Foot. The leaſt degree of true Godlineſs, and holy Love to God, doth ſincerely, yet not perfectly mortify, hate, expel, and war againſt all Sin, and deſires to be by Grace ſinleſs and impeccable. A Perſon may ſincerely love God, and yet through errour and miſtake ſay he doth not, and may have godly Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and yet complain as if he had none; <hi>Pſal.</hi> 77.10. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22.10. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.15, 16.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. X. <hi>Of the Image of God.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. CHriſt conſidered as God, is the eſſential, ſubſtantial, and increated Image and Form of God the Father by Nature, not by Grace. Chriſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered as Man, exalted at God's right Hand, is by Grace, not by Nature, the Image of Himſelf, as God Equal with the Father and the Holy Ghoſt, in a ſpecial and peculiar Senſe above all both Angels and Men; and yet he is but one Image of God rightly conceived, as he is but one Chriſt. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.6. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.15. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.3, 9, 13. The Divine Eſſence, as it is in God the Father, begetteth the Divine Eſſence as it is in God the Son: Yet will it not hence follow that there are two Divine Eſſences, but only that the Divine Eſſence as it is in God the Father unbegotten, is not the Divine Eſſence as it is in God the Son begotten. Which is certainly true: For Unbegot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and Begotten are eternally divers and diſtinct. This eternal Generation of God the Son is not a Work of God, but it is the Nature of God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and had been if there had never been Work of God. God the Father is not <hi>Autotheos</hi> of and from Himſelf, and therefore God the Son is not. God ſimply is, and cannot but be, and ſimply to be, is to be God. <hi>Exod.</hi> 3.14. The Creature ſimply is not, but the Creature as ſuch is dependent on God, and as compared with him it is as Nothing, yea leſs than Nothing and Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40.17, 18. Sin indeed is abſolutely, ſimply, and eternally of it ſelf, exceeding ſinful. <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.44. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.13. But God is not Sin. He is ſimply Firſt, and ſimply Firſt is from none.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As to Life Temporal, ungodly Men, as Men, are the Image of God no leſs than godly Men. Thence Murder is ſo great a Sin, becauſe thereby contrary to the Law and Light of Nature, the Image of God in Man, as to this preſent Life, is extinct, a living Man is turned into a dead Corpſe, and no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> dead can be the Image of the living God, <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.6. As to Life <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>eavenly Converſation by Faith, only godly Men and Women, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Image of God, and ungodly Perſons are the Image of the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:175184:13"/>Devil. As to Conjugal Society, the Husband is the Image and Glory of God, and not the Wife, he being her Head, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.3, 7. In reſpect of natural Generation, Parents are the Image of God, and not Children. In reſpect of domeſtical Rule and Government, Maſters are the Image of God, and not Servants. In reſpect of earthly Soveraignty, Kings, and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Civil Rulers are the Image of God, and not Subjects. Saints Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant, as Triumphant and by Grace impeccable, are the Image of God, ſo as Saints Militant are not. Damned Men, as Men, and intellectual Beings, are againſt their Will the Image of God for ever; becauſe they do againſt their will fulfil God's Law, by bearing the eternal Penalty thereof, due for their Sin.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Soul is truly a Spiritual Subſtance, and yet truly material, not to our bodily Senſes outwardly, but to our Faith inwardly. For the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition is not between Spiritual and Material, but between Spiritual and Carnal. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.1. and 9.11. <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.27. Spiritual, Inviſible, and Eternal Things are incomparably and tranſcendently Material, they are the Matters of God, and of greateſt Conſequence and Importance to our Souls through Faith. The Soul is not the Form of Man, but the Body is the Form of Man, and the Soul is the quickening Life and Spirit. In beholding a Corpſe and dead Man, we behold the Form and Appearance of Man, but we do not behold the Soul. The Soul is the Image of God, and therefore it cannot conſiſt in a dead Form. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.20. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Soul and Body are truly diſtinct as Principal and Inſtrumental, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and the outward Man, but they are not two eſſential and compoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Parts of Man. For Man is the Image of God, who being without Parts and Compoſition, ſo muſt needs be his Image. As all in God is God, ſo all in the Image of God is the Image of God. Every Man as to his natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Subſtance is ſimply a Man, and not a Brute, and therefore he muſt needs be uncompounded. For to be ſimply a Man, and yet compounded, is a Contradiction. Indeed the Body by it ſelf conſiſts of many Parts: It will not therefore follow that it is onely one Part of Man. For if it be one only, it is not many. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.16. As to Life Eternal the Soul is the Man, not as excluding the Body: but the Welfare of the Body is bound up in the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Welfare of the Soul. If the Soul be ſafe, all is ſafe: If that be loſt, all is loſt, and the Man is undone for ever. As to Life Temporal, the Body is the Man, not as excluding the Soul; but as it is in and by the Body that Man doth viſibly live and converſe on Earth as a Man and not a Brute, and the Body being dead, the Man is dead as to this preſent Life. And therefore not one Part of Chriſt, but Chriſt Himſelf in reſpect of his Body was crucifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, dead, buried, and lay in the Grave. <hi>Come, ſee the place where the Lord lay. Mat.</hi> 28.6.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:175184:14"/>
            <p n="5">5. Every Artificial Image of Chriſt as God is an Idol: and every Artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Image of Chriſt as Man, is Superſtition; and if adored, then it is Idolatry. Chriſt as Man is holy, and Holineſs may not be ſet forth by a dead Image or Picture. Only holy Men and Women in this World as holy, are the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of Chriſt as he is Man. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.29. Any other Image of Chriſt as Man, is a lie, and not the Image of Chriſt. Chriſt is truly a Man, but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al a ſpecial Man differing in kind from all other Men, becauſe he only is by miraculous Conception in the Womb of a Virgin, He only is the Propitiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for the Sins of the whole World, He only as Man is exalted at God's right Hand above all both Angels and Men: They may be ſet forth by an Artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Image or Picture, but ſo may not Chriſt as Man. The only true ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting forth of Chriſt as Man, is by the Word and Sacraments through Faith: becauſe as Man he differs <hi>in ſpecie</hi> in kind from all other Men.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. XI. <hi>Of the Church and Commonwealth.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. THE Holy Catholick Church which we believe, as diſtinct from the elect Angels, conſiſts of the whole number of God's Elect in all Ages, not as excluſive of what is good and commendable in Hypocrites, Hereticks, Apoſtates, and Heathens, but as liking and loving all that is good and lovely in whomſoever. This Church began in penitent <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> they two were the firſt Church of the redeemed. Upon the increaſe and multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of new Converts, and Souls regenerate, more were added to the Church ſucceſſively like as when an Infant is born into the World, there is one more added to the Society of Mankind, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.47. The Apoſtles Commiſſion was not to make a new Church differing in ſubſtance from what had been before, and was in being at the time of Chriſt's Aſcenſion, but to preſerve that Church which he left on Earth, and by Apoſtolical Preaching, and Endeavours, to enlarge and add to it, and ſo to make <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentile</hi> one in Chriſt Jeſus. Outward Variations, ſuited to the Exegencies of the Church, in its Militant State, do not alter the intrinſecal Nature, Eſſence, and Unity of the Church, which is the ſame for ſubſtance in all Ages. But becauſe <hi>Abel</hi> is the firſt who died in Faith, and of whoſe Righteouſneſs there is expreſs mention, therefore the Holy Catholick Church is fitly reckoned from him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Church and Commonwealth are not two independent Societies, but the Church, as ſuch, is a holy Commonwealth, ſimply dependent upon God through Chriſtian Faith, as to Life eternal: And upon the Prince as ſole Supream, under God, over all in his Dominions, as to Life Temporal, and Coercive rule by the Sword. Look as <hi>Homo</hi> being a Man includes <hi>Animal,</hi> being a Living Creature: So the Church includes human Society,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:175184:14"/>as being nothing but Mankind ſanctified, by Faith in Chriſt. The Power and Authority of Chriſt, as Man, exalted at God's right Hand over all, is ſimply dependent upon God: And therefore all the Power and Authority of the Church muſt needs be ſimply dependent, miniſterial, and ſubordinate; and whatſoever Church claims to it ſelf Power ſimply independent, by that very claim it is proved to be Anti-chriſtian, that Man of Sin, and Son of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, who exalts himſelf above God, and above the Prince his Vice-gerent on Earth, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.3, 4.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Church is not two, Univerſal and Particular, Inviſible and Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; but the Church is ſimply one, as God is one; admitting of juſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, but no Diviſion. It is one Whole or Univerſal, as comprizing all the Parts: But one Whole or Univerſal, as diſtinct from all the Parts, is only Notion and Conceit, as a Man in the Moon, or Caſtle in the Air, a meer Chimera. We ſee thoſe Men and Women who are the Church Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant, but that which makes them the Church Militant we do not ſee, but believe. The Church is plain and manifeſt to thoſe who believe, as the Sun at Noon-day, is to ſeeing Men: But he who believeth not, makes God a Lyar, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.10. and God being made a Lyar, the Church muſt needs be made a Lyar too.</p>
            <p n="4">4. It will not ſtand with Chriſtian Faith, Hope, and Love, to live di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided in Heart and Converſation, from any the leaſt Member of Chriſt and true Chriſtian, who is evidently and apparently ſo, ſo far as Man can judg. We cannot be more holy than God, more pure then Chriſt: Whom he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives, we are to receive, or we cannot expect to be received by him. The Communion of Saints is an Article of Faith, unalterably fixed by God as to the ſubſtance of it, and it conſiſts in Chriſtian Faith, Hope, and Love: Theſe are to the Church, and every Member thereof, what the Soul is to the Body. But ſaving Chriſtian Faith, Hope, and Love, we are to become all Things to all Men, and bear all Things rather than rend and divide the Church by nefarious and lewd Schiſm. Ungodly Chriſtians, conſidered as Ungodly, are not Chriſtians, and Members of the Church: But Ungodly Chriſtians, conſidered not as Ungodly, but as Chriſtians, are a ſort of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians and Church-Members, and are not meer Heathens and Perſons with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out: They are of the Church, and yet they are not the Church, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.6.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Loyalty is a Fundamental in Religion, as without which human So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety cannot ſubſiſt, and no human Society no Religion. Human Society cannot ſubſiſt without ſome to Rule and ſome to be Ruled. If the Ruled may reſiſt and riſe in Rebellion againſt their lawful Rulers, ſet over them by God, Mankind is no longer a Society, but a Rout; and a Foundation is laid for endleſs War, Deſolation, and Confuſion of all Things. The Nature of a Fundamental in Religion is to expel its Contrary, as Light doth Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:175184:15"/>As then no Man can in the ſame Inſtant be both Godly and Ungodly: So can no Man in the ſame Inſtant be both Loyal and Diſloyal. Loyalty is not Loyalty unleſs it be ſo out of Conſcience, either Natural and Common, ſuch as may be in Heathens and Men not Regenerate; or Supernatural and Special, ſuch as is in the Regenerate. He that is only Loyal out of Self-ends and for Worldly Intereſt, is not Loyal before God. Human Law, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as Human, cannot bind the Conſcience: But conſidered as ſubſervient to the Divine Law, ſo it is in a large Senſe Divine, and as Divine, it binds the Conſcience: For all that lies in us, we are to live peaceably with all Men. Yet where the Thing enacted and enjoyned is not intrinſecally neceſſary to the publick Good, there a Man hath his choice, whether to do the thing, or to pay the Penalty. In no caſe may we reſiſt Authority Supream and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate: In no caſe may we obey Man againſt God. Therefore when no way is left, but either we muſt Suffer, or Sin; we muſt patiently and meekly Suffer, and lay down our Lives, rather than reſiſt, or allow the leaſt Sin.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. XII. <hi>Of Original Sin, the ſtate of Infants, and their Baptiſm.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. AS to Life Temporal there are in the Soul Habits diſtinct from Act, and by frequent Acts Men get a Habit. But as to Eternity there is no ſuch Diſtinction: For the Soul as being a ſpiritual and immortal Subſtance, is the Image of God, and is therefore ever in act inviſibly. From the time that it is firſt formed in the Womb, it ceaſeth not to live a Life dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, in kind, from Brutes; and while in the Body, is ſtill upon its way to Eternity, and either it is Godly, and ſo in the way to Heaven, and inviſibly active for God: or it is Ungodly, and ſo in the way to Hell, and inviſibly active againſt him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If God ſhall give unto <hi>Adam,</hi> after his Fall, Children by natural Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, and ſhall not alſo give them inward heavenly Grace, and ſuperna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Regeneration, it is moſt certain that inwardly and inviſibly they will be Graceleſs and Unregenerate: As Graceleſs and Unregenerate they are Unholy, dead in Sin, and full of enmity againſt God, and ſo dying, it is above me to prove that they have not in them the never-dying Worm. This Original Sin, in Infants, is neither from God, nor from <hi>Adam,</hi> nor from their immediate Parents; but it is wholly from themſelves inwardly and unſearchably, neither by natural neceſſity, nor after the ſimilitude of <hi>Adam</hi>'s Tranſgreſſion, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.14. but by legal Neceſſity. Which is a ſort of Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity innocently and unſearchably permitted by God, but not willed by him,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:175184:15"/>and is not avoidable by either Parents or Children, without ſupernatural Grace in Chriſt Jeſus. Even as ungodly grown Men, in their Sleep, while their Sleep laſteth, are unavoidably and inexcuſably ungodly.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The adequate ground of Hope concerning the whole Off-ſpring of <hi>Adam,</hi> is Divine Election in Chriſt Jeſus. If we bottom it not entirely up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this, we muſt needs bottom it upon Reprobation, there being no mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, or third, imaginable. Elect and Reprobate, as Godly and Ungodly, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide all the World. And to bottom Hope of Salvation upon Reprobation, is to deſtroy Hope. All the Infants of Godly Parents, both, or one, dying in meer Infancy, we may well think are elect and ſaved, as a Part of that holy Catholick Church which conſiſts of the Elect in all Ages: And of this Baptiſm, to me, ſeems to be a ſacred Sign and Seal. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.21. Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly Chriſtians, as hath been ſaid, conſidered not as Ungodly, but as Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, are a ſort of Chriſtians and not meer Heathens. The Infants of ſuch being brought unto us by the Parents, or ſome other Chriſtian in their ſtead, themſelves being reaſonably letted, with deſire to have them baptiſed, I conceive it is our Duty, as we are Chriſt's Miniſters, in Obedience to his Command, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19, 20. Well ſuiting with the Grounds of Faith, the approved Practice of the Church before Chriſt's Incarnation, the Words and Example of Chriſt touching Infants, <hi>Mark.</hi> 10.13, 14, 15, 16. and the Practice of the Apoſtles in baptizing Houſholds, to baptize there Infants. And if they ſhall be taken away in meer Infancy by Death, we may well think that they alſo are Elect and Saved, and that of ſuch alſo is the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God. Though the Parents have not Godly Sincerity, yet a ſort of Sincerty they have, and they do really and not diſſemblingly deſire Baptiſm for their Infants, and are truly glad of it. Either ſome Infants are eternal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, elect and endued with the Holy Ghoſt ſavingly, or not. If yea, can a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Man forbid Water, that theſe ſhould not be baptized, which are eternal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly elect, and endued with the Holy Ghoſt ſavingly, as well as grown Men? <hi>Act.</hi> 10.47, 48. If not, then all Infants are eternally reprobate and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, the Infant Jeſus not excepted. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42.1. <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.35.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Contempt of Baptiſm is damnable in the Contemners: but In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants cannot contemn it. <hi>Chriſt ſent me not to baptize, but to preach the Goſpel.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.17. The Goſpel, that is, Life eternal through Faith in Chriſt, is ſimply neceſſary for all Perſons, in all Places, at all Times, from the Fall of <hi>Adam</hi> to the End of the World; But ſo is not Baptiſm. If the Perſon die inwardly holy and regenerate, as he may, though not baptized, he is undoubtedly ſaved.</p>
            <p n="5">5. If the baptized Infant be not inwardly holy and regenerate (as all are not) then I conceive it is not in a State of Salvation, it is not ſet free from Guilt eternal, yet is its Baptiſm as ordained of God, and diſpenſed by his
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:175184:16"/>Miniſter neither Nullity nor Mockery, but a Divine Bond, Oath, and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant laid upon the Infant to be what all the Off-ſpring of <hi>Adam</hi> by God's Law indiſpenſably are bound to be, truly holy, and God's faithful Servant. Either its Regeneration is future, or it is not. If yea, then Baptiſm is a ſure Pledg, Seal, and Token that it is future. If not, then the Infant will outlive the State of Infancy, and will live and die ungodly, and periſh; in which Caſe his Baptiſm will be an everlaſting Witneſs againſt him, it being ſuppoſed that his Conſcience was privy to it. Baptiſm is a Seal of the Covenant of Grace, which Covenant importeth God's Purpoſe to give Perſeverance and Salvation to all the Regenerate, and to Regenerate ſuch and ſo many, as he from Eternity foreſees will, by his Grace, and Free-gift, ſincerely believe. And yet, while Unregenerate, they are in a State of Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. As to Life Temporal, and Humane Society on Earth, ungodly Men have Power over their own Will, and Liberty to act, or not to act, as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves liſt, and they can, if they will refrain from all Sin outwardly, and do all Good outwardly, and be blameleſs before Men. But as to Life Eternal, and Heavenly Converſation, they have no Power, they are dead in Sin, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Power of Satan, their Power is Impotency, Sin hath Dominion over them, they are not Lords, but Slaves, and lorded over by their Luſts; and if God ſhall not prevent them with his Heavenly Grace, it is certain that they will never deſerve it. Therefore the firſt ſtep to Salvation is holy Deſpair there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of by all that we of our ſelves can do without God's eternal Grace in Chriſt. And look what is Firſt in Divinity, that ſame is Laſt, even All in All.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="13" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. XIII. <hi>Of the Lord's Supper.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. LOok as all in God is God without Parts and Compoſition: So all in the Lord's Supper is the Lord's Supper. Conſidered as a Supper, ſo the whole is viſible, Food for the Belly, eaten and drunk with the Mouth outwardly: Conſidered as the Lord's Supper ſo the whole is inviſible, Food for the Soul, eaten and drunk with the Heart inwardly. There may be the Lord's Supper without ſaving Belief: but not without Belief. For he that believeth not, makes God a Liar, and by Conſequence the Sacrament a Lie alſo. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.10.</p>
            <p n="2">2. There is no Change at all of the Elements by Conſecration, but only Religious Uſe. If the Religious Uſe of Things do neceſſarily infer a Change in the Things uſed, then God muſt needs be changed, and then he is not God. We uſe God's Name religiouſly, and God's Name is God Himſelf, as named by this or that Name, Jehovah, Lord, God. <hi>I am the Lord, that
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:175184:16"/>is my Name. Iſa.</hi> 42.8. What Change is by Conſecration, is in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municants, not at all in the Elements. Conſecration importeth in all Godly Communicants, a real Heavenly Change as to Converſation, Converſion from Sin to God, they are new Creatures, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.17. This heavenly Change they evidence, exerciſe, and ſhew forth at the Lord's Table, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious partaking of the Elements in Remembrance of Chriſt crucified. All Change in the Elements by Conſecration is ſimply repugnant to intellectual Senſe in all Men, and is therefore ſimply incredible.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Theſe Words, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> as underſtood without Chriſtian Faith, are falſe and abſurd: But as underſtood through Chriſtian Faith, they are indeed myſterious, yet Superlatively plain, true, apt, and proper. The Lord's Supper is truly a Figure, as is Baptiſm, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.21. yet not a Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bal and Rhetorical Figure common to Us and Heathens, but a Divine, Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtial, and Myſterious Figure inſtituted by Chriſt, and not underſtood with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Chriſtian Belief, which Heathens have not. In Points that concern us as Men, in common with all the World, Chriſt ſpake with the Vulgar, and ſo as to be underſtood of very Heathens. But in Points myſterious and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernatural, as is the Doctrine of the Lord's Supper, he ſpake above the Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, and ſo, as not to be underſtood aright without Faith, which Heathens have not. Ungodly Communicants, conſidered as Ungodly, do not eat Chriſt's Body, but inwardly contemn and ſhut their Hearts againſt it: And thus their partaking doth differ in kind from the inward partaking of the Godly. But Ungodly Communicants, conſidered as Communicants, do with their Mouth outwardly eat the Bread, which is really, and not chime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rically, yet ſacramentally and ſymbolically the Body of Chriſt, no leſs than do Godly Communicants outwardly: And thus their partaking is the ſame for kind with the partaking of the Godly. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.1, 2, 3, 4, 5.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Unto worthy Communicants the Lord's Supper is the Communion of the Lord's Body and Blood, the holy Memorial of his Death, heavenly Nouriſhment for the Soul, a ſure Pledge, Seal, Sign, and Token of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of Sin, Perſeverance, and Life eternal, and a Divine Engagement to Watchfulneſs and holy Fear of Apoſtacy. No Godly Man doth partake un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily; he may partake not ſo worthily as ſome do, but the leaſt degree of true Godlineſs doth produce a degree of worthy communicating, differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but in meaſure and degree from the moſt Godly Communicants. Unto unworthy Communicants the Lord's Supper, through their own Sin, is a Seal of their Damnation, if they die without ſound Repentance: And in the mean time it layeth a Divine Bond and Engagement upon them inſtantly to repent. If their Repentance, by God's eternal Decree, be future, then the Lord's Supper is a Divine Sign and Seal that it is future: If their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance be not future, then they will die in their Sins, and periſh, and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:175184:17"/>will remember with eternal Self-tormenting Anguiſh, in Hell, their partaking without Godly Sincerity. Thoſe who contend, that Men Unregenerate ſin leſs in not coming, than in coming to the Lord's Table, do yet expreſly grant: <hi>But yet they that do come unworthily and unwarrantably, do find that there, which tendeth to their Converſion, and frequently effecteth it. Mr.</hi> B. <hi>in his Diſputations of Right to Sacraments,</hi> pag. 31, 32. And they who contend that the Unregenerate ſin leſs in coming, than in not coming, do yet hold and contend, that the Perſons ſo come muſt be adult, baptized, orthodox and not heretical, free from enormous Crimes and Scandals, before Men. The bare Elements, as diſtinct from the Word, can neither convert nor confirm. But the Word, as diſtinct from the Elements, and giving being to the whole Sacramental Service, may, through God's Grace, prove effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al for ſound Converſion of the Unconverted, and certainly will be effectual for building up of the Converted.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The Fleſh and Manhood of Chriſt is, under God, the prime inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Cauſe of Life eternal, to the Godly in all Ages, through Faith: As ſuch, his Fleſh is heavenly Meat, and his Blood is heavenly Drink, and we, through Faith, do really and not chimerically, ſpiritually and not corporally eat and drink it. What is eaten, in that it is eaten, muſt be really preſent: For no Man can eat a thing that is abſent. There is Relation between the Manhood of Chriſt and the whole intellectual World, as between ſole Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream under God, and Subjects: This Relation is real and not imaginary, eternal and not temporal: From Eternity it was future, and it remains to Eternity by the free Pleaſure of God. What is eternal is truly infinite, above all Predicaments, and conſequently above Time and Place, yet not contrary thereto. Things related are <hi>ſimul naturâ,</hi> intrinſecally together, not in Place outwardly, but in Truth and Reality inwardly, above both Time and Place. Only this is to be noted, that though the Manhood of Chriſt be ſole Supream under God, over all both Angels and Men, as he is exalted at God's right Hand, yet only elect Angels and Men be his Loyal and Obedient Subjects. There are, who hold ſome things neceſſary to the Integrity of the Sacrament, but not to its Eſſence, as breaking the Bread. But the Scripture hath no ſuch diſtinction, and indeed it is repugnant to the Nature of God, who is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Eſſence, and in him is infinite Integrity: Therefore there cannot poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly be Eſſence and not Integrity. Therefore breaking the Bread, is to be reckoned among thoſe things which are not intrinſecally neceſſary to the Being and Integrity of the Lord's Supper. As to which the general rule is, to obſerve the way and cuſtom of the Church where a Man ſhall come and abide. But as to the Cup, no power on Earth may deprive the People of it.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="14" type="chapter">
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:175184:17"/>
            <head>CHAP. XIV. <hi>Of Divine Worſhip, and Idolatry.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. THat there is a God, and that he is to be worſhipped as God, is inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebly written in the Heart of every Man; for every Man is either Godly or Ungodly: To be Godly, is to be a worſhipper of God in Spirit and Truth: To be Ungodly, is to have an inward Senſe and Conviction that there is a God, and not to worſhip and glorify him as God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The true God, is God the Father not incarnate, God the Son incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, God the Holy Ghoſt not incarnate; the Saviour of all Men, ſpecially of them that believe: Any other God is an Idol, and not the true God. To worſhip this true God, is penitently to confeſs our Sins, to call upon His Name, and pray unto him for ſpiritual and corporal Bleſſings, to give him Thanks for his Mercies, to ſwear by his Name, to vow and covenant our Souls to him, to believe his Holy Word, to truſt in him for Life Eternal, to walk as in his Sight and Preſence, to eſteem him incomparably Excellent, to prefer his Favour, Honour, and Glory, and the doing of his Will, before our Life, and Friends, and Eſtate, and all worldly and temporal Things; to have clean Hearts and pure Conſciences, and in all things to make it our chief care and buſineſs to pleaſe him, and to obtain eternal Reward and Bleſſedneſs, by righteous, ſober, and godly Converſation. In the Worſhip of God the Soul is Principal, and the Body is Inſtrumental, and the ſame thing is eſſentially both Act and Object: For there cannot be the right Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God without Self-denial; according to that of the Pſalmiſt <hi>Not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us, O Lord, not unto us, but unto thy Name be all the Glory: For of Him, and through Him, and to Him are all things, Pſal.</hi> 115. 1. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.36. Now Self-denial is both Act and Object. Accordingly, in all Idolatry, the Soul is Principal, and the Body is Inſtrumental, and the ſame thing is both Act and Object: For in every Idolater there is regnant Self-eſteem, Self-will, Self-love, and Self-confidence, repugnant to heavenly Self-denial, and Holy Truſt in God. The Idolater putteth truſt in his own Heart, that tho he give the Glory due to God, in Chriſt only, to another, tho he worſhip God in and by meer Creatures, and not in and by Chriſt only, yet he ſhall be ſaved, and God will accept him: This is Self-deluſion and falſe Truſt; and Self<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deluſion and Self-confidence, is both Act and Object.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>An Idol is nothing in the World,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.4. That is, as I conceive, ſet aſide the inward ungodly Luſt, and falſe Belief, which is in Man's Heart, and there is no ſuch thing as an Idol, nor can be. Every Creature of God is Good, Man is a ſpecial Creature of God, and therefore muſt needs be
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:175184:18"/>ſpecially Good. The Goodneſs of Man conſiſts in the inward Rectitude of his Mind, and hevenly dependence upon god, and Reſignation to his Will, and truſt in him for Life eternal. When contrary-wiſe, Man refuſeth to be guided by God, as to Life eternal, and putteth truſt in his own Heart, and not in God, for Life eternal, and loveth himſelf rather than God; now Man comes to have Idols in his Heart, and committeth ſpiritual Whoredom and Adultery. Some make the Belly their God, ſome Idolize Money, ſome worldly Glory, ſome Beauty, ſome Learning, ſome their Errours, ſome Angels and departed Saints, ſome Images: Theſe are various ways of Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, but ſtill it is the mind within, as ungodly, which makes the Idol, and all Idolatry whatſoever is a tranſcendent Vice, the worſhip of a falſe God, and is repugnant to Holy Belief in God. As God is not two, a material God, and a formal God: So Idolatry is not two, material and formal, but all Idolatry is a breach of the firſt Commandment, and repugnant to godly Sincerity. No Man doth or can in the commiſſion of Idolatry intend to commit it, but really he doth commit it, he doth that which by the Divine Law is Idolatry. The commiſſion of Idolatry, and intention to commit it, differ ſpecifically, and cannot poſſibly concur in one and the fame indiviſible Act, as one and the ſame indiviſible Act cannot poſſibly be two Acts.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The ſubſtance of Divine Worſhip is unalterably fixed by God, and all addition to it, and all diminution from it, is Idolatry, a Deifying of Man's Underſtanding and Will, and ſetting it above the Underſtanding and Will of God. But there are many things reſpecting the outward Mode and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of God's Worſhip, about which the Scripture gives only general Rules, the fitting whereof to particular Caſes, is left to Man's Wiſdom and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, dependently upon God, as Judg of all the World. Touching the ſubſtance of God's Worſhip, nothing is a Duty but what hath a Divine Command, and plain Warrant in God's Word: Touching Things in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves indifferent, and variable, nothing is ſinful but what is plainly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden by God, what is not forbidden, is of it ſelf Lawful.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Religiouſly to invocate Angels and departed Saints is very Idolatry: but bare deſiring their Prayers, I conceive, is not Idolatry. Superſtition it is, vain and erroneous Deſire it is; but tho all Idolatry be Superſtition, yet all Superſtition and vain Deſire is not Idolatry: But if Superſtition reign, then it is Idolatry before God, tho not before Men. And then doth Superſtition and Errour reign, when Perſons lay their Salvation on it, and truſt in their Errour for Life Eternal. Bare deſiring the Prayer of Angels and departed Saints, is not Prayer and Invocation in the ſtrict ſenſe, and therefore, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, it is not Idolatry. Tho all Prayer be Deſire, yet all Deſire is not Prayer in the ſtrict ſenſe. Bare deſiring the Prayer of Angels and departed Saints, doth ſuppoſe them to know what indeed they do not know, and ſo
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:175184:18"/>it is erroneous and vain Deſire: but it doth not neceſſarily ſuppoſe them to be ſimply Omniſcient, which only God is. Finally, it is a Point of Faith, and the very ſum of the Bible, that ſince the Fall of Man, all Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Approach to God, is to be in and through Chriſt only: They which do otherwiſe, are guilty of flat Idolatry.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="15" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. XV. <hi>Of the Scripture.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. THough heavenly Truth was not put into Writing outwardly till the time of <hi>Moſes,</hi> yet was it from the beginning, ſupernaturally written in the Heart of <hi>Adam</hi> in Innocency, and being extinguiſhed by his Fall, it was renewed in him in ſaving meaſure by heavenly Regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion after his Fall, and by this way kept ſafe in the inward Records of the Heart, and tranſmitted unto the time of <hi>Moſes.</hi> When he by divine Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment and Inſpiration, did firſt put heavenly Truth into writing out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, this did not alter the intrinſecal nature of it: For heavenly Truth as written in the Heart, and in the Bible, is but one and the ſame Truth diverſly written, perfectly in the Bible, truly, but not perfectly in the Heart of Man ſince the Fall, and the entrance of Sin into the World.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Whether all the Books of the Old and New Teſtament, as we reckon them, be Canonical Scripture; and whether every Word and Sentence there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in be exactly tranſlated, this is not matter of Divine Belief, nor doth Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation lie on it, ſo as to damn all that err herein; but it is matter of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Science and Teſtimony, as ſubſervient to Divine Belief. Human Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and Teſtimony, conſidered as repugnant to Divine Belief, is not Science and Teſtimony, but a Lie: Conſidered as ſubſervient vient to Divine Belief, ſo it is in a large ſenſe truly divine, and as divine it is infallible. And thus the Scripture is the ſupream Judg and adequate Standard in Controverſies of Faith. The ſum of the Scripture is, Repentance and Remiſſion of Sins through Faith in Chriſt, according to the eternal Purpoſe of God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther not incarnate, the Son incarnate, the Holy Ghoſt not incarnate: This is al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſaving Evidence in one, not as excluſive of things ſubſervient, but as ſuppoſing and comprizing them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. With reſpect to Life Temporal and Human Converſe, Words are not Things, but ſigns of Mens inward Thoughts, and the great Arbiter of Speech is Uſe, <hi>quem penes arbitrium eſt, &amp; jus &amp; norma loquendi.</hi> With reſpect to Life eternal, and heavenly Converſation by Faith, Words are Things, and therefore we are commanded to hold faſt the form of ſound Words; and Chriſt ſaith, <hi>By thy Words thou ſhalt be juſtified, and by thy
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:175184:19"/>Words thou ſhalt be condemned.</hi> God hath ſet us a Standard for all our Words, unto which none may add, from which none may diminiſh, under pain of Damnation. The great Myſtery of Godlineſs is, <hi>The Word was made Fleſh, Joh.</hi> 1.14. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.18, 19. <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.37. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.13. Indeed, where there is an agreement in Subſtance, diverſity in Speech for Peace-ſake is to be born with. But there can be no agreement in Subſtance without the Scripture as the ſole ſupream Judg, and perfect Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard as to all things concerning the Glory of God, and the eternal Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Soul. If we go from this we ſhall not know where to fix, a Foundation is laid for infinite proceeding, and ſo for Atheiſm and Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of all things.</p>
            <p n="4">4. There are who write, that all Words that Man can ſpeak of God, at leaſt, except Being and Subſtance, are improper or metaphorical. But cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly this is a great Error: For tho God be above all our Words and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, yet he is not above and contrary to Himſelf, he cannot be the Author of Sin, he is not God improperly and metaphorically. God is good, and there are good Angels and Men: both theſe are true and proper. But in the ſenſe that God is good, eſſentially, independently, inderivatively, the Author of all Good, ſo none is good but God: Every Creature, as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent on God, is good, and uſeful to his Glory, and the Salvation of his Elect by Chriſt: But the whole Creation, as compared with God, is as nothing, it is leſs than nothing, and Vanity: <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40.17, 18. All Words importing Excellency and Perfection, and no way importing Imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection and Impiety, do agree to God ſimply, incomparably, tranſcendent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, eternally, infinitely, moſt truly, really, and properly, and not at all to Angels and Men, as compared with God. <hi>Dat propriae ſimilem tranſlata metaphora vocem.</hi> Things heavenly and eternal may be ſet forth by world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and temporal Similitudes: But ſo, that things heavenly and eternal are the Standard, <hi>Judex ſui &amp; obliqui.</hi> Thus Chriſt's Fleſh, as eaten by Faith, is Meat indeed; and his Blood, as drunk by Faith, is Drink indeed; not metaphorical, rhetorical, verbal, improper, and imaginary Food; but moſt real, heavenly, ſolid, ſubſtantial, divine, tranſcendent, incomparably ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent, and eternal Food for the Soul: and all worldly and temporal Food for the Body, as compared with, and repugnant to it, is not Food at all, but Dung, Loſs, and Damnation eternal; but as ſubſervient to it, it is true and proper Food for the Body, God's good Creature, and worthy of Thankſgiving.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The Fountain-cauſe of ſo much doleful Contention among Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans touching Religion, is, their leaving the Simplicity that is in Chriſt, and guiding themſelves by that Philoſophy and School-Sophiſtry, which the Scripture calls vain Deceit; 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.3. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.8. Philoſophy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:175184:19"/>as ſubſervient to Life Eternal by Faith in Chriſt, is not Philoſophy, but Chriſtianity largely taken. Philoſophy conſidered as repugnant to Life Eternal by Faith in Chriſt, is damnable Impiety, the Mother of Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy and Diviſion, that Wiſdom which is from beneath, which is earthly, ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual, and deviliſh. Philoſophers, as ſuch, treat of God<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Man, of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, of Truth, of Good, of Unity, of Vertue, of Nature, of Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, of what not? not as Chriſtians, but as Philoſophers; not by the Light of Faith in Chriſt, but by the Light of Nature; which in Points of Faith is very Darkneſs. And ſo the whole Doctrine of Philoſophers, as ſuch, is falſe, a meer Building without a Foundation: Becauſe Chriſt is the firſt and the laſt in all true Knowledg, as being God the Son incarnate, and God is All in All. This Philoſophers, as ſuch, be ignorant of, and do not build Science upon Chriſt, the ſole Foundation of Science by Faith; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.11. and ſo they err in the Foundation, and all the Science of Philoſophers, as ſuch, is falſe Science, repugnant to Faith in Chriſt.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="16" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. XVI. <hi>Containing a Confutation of ſundry Errors held by too many School-men, Philoſophers, and Divines of all Parties, by which Controverſies are kept up and perpetuated.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>Error</hi> 1. THE Man Chriſt is God, in the Concrete; but not the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of Chriſt, in the Abſtract. Before the Incarnation Chriſt was ſimple, uncompounded, impartial, and but one Nature: After Incarnation he is not ſimple, but compounded, and conſiſteth of two diſtinct Natures, as two eſſential Parts. <hi>Confutation.</hi> The Man Chriſt is indeed God, yet not as he is Man: And the Manhood of Chriſt, is that holy thing which was born of the Bleſſed Virgin, and is truly called the Son of God, and this Son of God is very God, the Son incarnate; <hi>Luke</hi> 1.35. <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.1, 14, 18. Jeſus Chriſt is the ſame yeſterday, and to day, and for ever; after Incarnation as before, and before as after; <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.8. with this cautious meaning: Before Incarnation he was Jeſus Chriſt, as from Eternity purpoſed in time to be incarnate: After Incarnation, he is the ſame Jeſus Chriſt as incarnate, according to that Purpoſe. If he be at all compounded, then he is not ſimply Chriſt, and then he is a Deceiver: For Simple and Compounded are contraries, as Light and Darkneſs, Truth and Falſhood. If Chriſt conſiſt of Parts, then he is not ſimply impartial, and then he cannot judge the World in Righteouſneſs, but muſt needs ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove Murder in <hi>David,</hi> and condemn it in <hi>Cain;</hi> which is Blaſphemy. The Manhood of Chriſt is not one part, or one half of Chriſt, but it is
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:175184:20"/>Chriſt himſelf conſidered as Man: And the Godhead of Chriſt is Chriſt himſelf, conſidered as God, and yet he is but one Perſon, but one Chriſt; and the Nature of Chriſt, as he is God manifeſt in the Fleſh, and the Word made Fleſh, is but one, admitting of juſt Conception, but no Parts and Compoſition.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Error</hi> 2. All things in Nature are reducible to ten Predicaments, of which Relation is one. <hi>Confut.</hi> All things in Nature are reducible to one, which one is God; of whom, and through whom, and to whom are all things, and this God is our God for ever and ever; <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.36. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 48.14. Thus Relation is all in all, as being the Nature of God the Father not incarnate, the Son incarnate, the Holy Ghoſt not incarnate, eſſentially, and yet freely related to all Elect Angels and Men, as their God and Portion for ever.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Error</hi> 3. There are four diſtinct Cauſes of Juſtification, of Satisfaction for Sin, of the Sacraments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the efficient, the material, the formal, and the final Cauſe. <hi>Confut.</hi> All Cauſe touching Religion, and Life eternal, is either principal or ſupream, or inſtrumental and ſubſervient: And the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal and ſupream Cauſe is ſuperlatively, and tranſcendently, material, and of greateſt importance to our Faith and eternal Welfare, the Cauſe of Cauſes, even all in all. As to Worldly Science common to us and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, there is matter and form diſtinct: But as to Heavenly Science, by Faith (which Heathens have not) there is no ſuch diſtinction. For Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Science by Faith, conſiſteth not in Form, but in Power, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5. not in Shew and Appearance, but in Truth and Reality, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.20. It is one and the ſame thing which is the beginning and the end, the firſt and the laſt, the efficient and the final Cauſe, yet not in the ſame reſpects; <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.36. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.13.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Error</hi> 4. The Will of Man is effentially free, and eſſentially a Rational Appetite. <hi>Confut.</hi> The Will of Man is eſſentially rational and intellectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> but neither eſſentially free, nor eſſentially an Appetite. For if it be eſſentially free, then there can be no Hell: And if it be eſſentially an Appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite, then there can be no Heaven. Damned Men are Men, and in them is perfect intellectual human Will, as to natural Subſtance, but no free Will. They cannot be holy and happy if they would; <hi>Luke</hi> 16.26. All Freedom and Liberty is either temporal or eternal: in the Damned is neither, they cannot but implacably hate God, and will Annihilation rather than eternal Damnation. In the ſtate of perfect Felicity, there ſhall be in all bleſſed Men, perfect rational and intellectual Will, but no Appetite, no Deſire, no Wiſh, no want of any good thing, but perfect Satisfaction. Reſt, and Pleaſure for ever: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 17.15.</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:175184:20"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Error</hi> 5. The Divine Law is twofold, of Works, and of Faith; or the old and the new Law. <hi>Confut.</hi> The Divine Law is but one, as God the Author of it is one, admitting of juſt Conception, but no Diviſion. <hi>The Law was given by Moſes, but Grace and Truth came by Jeſus Chriſt, Joh.</hi> 1.17. Here the Law and Grace, as alſo <hi>Moſes</hi> and Chriſt are oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, yet not as contraries, but as divers, not as Satan and Chriſt, but as ſubſervient and ſupream. <hi>Moſes,</hi> as God's Miniſter, delivers the Law, by which is the knowledg of Sin, and Condemnation due for the ſame, to all the natural Off-ſpring of fallen <hi>Adam.</hi> And thus the Miniſtry of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the Law as diſtinct from, and relatively oppoſed to the Grace of the Goſpel in Chriſt, is a killing Letter, and the Miniſtration of Death and Condemnation, by reaſon of Sin in us; 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6, 7, 8, 9, 10. The Law and <hi>Moſes</hi> is not Jeſus Chriſt, they cannot purchaſe for us, and beſtow on us Goſpel-repentance, Pardon of Sin, Peace of Conſcience, and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Redemption: This is utterly above <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Law, as diſtinct from Chriſt, by themſelves to effect. But now Jeſus Chriſt, as diſtinct from, and relatively oppoſed to <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Law, is very God the Son incarnate, <hi>the Word made Fleſh,</hi> Joh. 1.14. and as ſuch, is Mediator; and as Mediator, he doth purchaſe the Church with his own Blood, and doth obtain for, and freely beſtow on <hi>Abel, Peter,</hi> and the reſt of the Elect, heavenly Righteouſneſs, Faith, Repentance, Pardon of Sin, Perſeverance, and eternal Redemption. Theſe are the higheſt Bleſſings and Priviledges, in reſpect whereof Chriſt, as Mediator, is to be worſhipped with ſupream Worſhip: otherwiſe he is a meer Man, nothing differing from <hi>Moſes,</hi> and our whole Faith is a Lie. Thus the Law and the Goſpel are diſtinct, and Faith in Chriſt doth not aboliſh, but doth eſtabliſh God's Law: <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.31. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19. and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="17" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. XVII. <hi>Of the Miniſtry, and Church-Diſcipline.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. THere may be a Church where is no Miniſter or Paſtor; but there cannot be a Church without a juſt eſteem of Paſtors and Miniſters, and care to have one where one is wanting. Where two or three are ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together in Chriſt's Name, there is he in the midſt of them: And where is Chriſt the Head, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Saints his Members by Faith, and Invocation, there is a Church both Name and Thing, tho there be no Paſtor or Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. But thoſe may not be ſaid to be gathered together in Chriſt's Name, who diſeſteem and contemn Paſtors and Miniſters.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:175184:21"/>
            <p n="2">2. Where Ordination may be had, conſiſtent with Faith and Piety, there it is to be had, and they who invade the Miniſterial Office without it, have no due Call from God, he never ſent them, ſuch Perſons do greatly offend againſt the Order and Unity of God's Church and choſen People, and are not to be owned and countenanced in their evil way. Where Ordination cannot be had, conſiſtent with Faith and Piety, there it is not to be had. There, if a Door be opened for preaching the Goſpel, one not ordained being able for the Work, and faithful, may preach, baptize, give the Lord's Supper, and do the whole Miniſterial Office, with purpoſe to have Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſo ſoon as with Faith and Piety it can be had. An open Door is the neceſſities and willingneſs of the People, with protection or connivance of the Magiſtrate, if poſſible.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In Ordination, God in Chriſt confers the whole Office as principal and ſupream by his Word: And the Perſon, or Perſons ordaining, confer the whole Office as inſtrumental and ſubordinate. Therefore it is not in the power of Men to ordain whom, and how they pleaſe, becauſe they or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain not as Lords, but as Stewards, they have no power touching this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but what is ſimply miniſterial, ſubordinate, and dependent. If therefore. God's Word for ſubſtance do not go along with the Ordination, it is null and void: and the ſame holds good as to Suſpending, Degrading, Silencing, and Prohibiting of Miniſters from doing the Miniſterial Work. Every Miniſter to be ordained ought to be a faithful Man, and able to teach others alſo: 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.1. For which cauſe thoſe unto whom it pertaineth to ordain and impoſe Hands, ought to uſe all poſſible Care and Circumſpection, and to lay Hands ſuddenly on none without due Exploration. He may be a va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid and juſtly authorized Miniſter, who is not truly Godly: And yet he that is not truly godly, can have no ſound Comfort in his Miniſtry, as being in a ſtate of Damnation; his Miniſtry may profit others, tho not himſelf. But yet all Care is to be uſed that Perſons to be ordained be truly godly, ſo far as Man can judg, and that alſo they be able to teach the People, and by good Doctrine guide Souls in the way to Heaven.</p>
            <p n="4">4. No Power on Earth may impoſe a Miniſter upon a People againſt their juſt liking: For what is againſt Juſtice, is againſt God. And no Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple may refuſe a Miniſter, tho unjuſtly impoſed on them, when they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, without general inconvenience and hazard of the publick Peace, reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy themſelves: For of two Evils, the leſſer is to be choſen. Provided the impoſed Miniſter be Orthodox and not Hereti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> tolerable and competent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly able for the Work in ſome meaſure. But Heretical, Schiſmatical, Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous, and Wolviſh Paſtors and Miniſters the People are bound to forſake and turn from. Where Miniſters Reſidence is neceſſary by Divine Law, there no Law of Man can diſpenſe with it: Where it is not neceſſary by
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:175184:21"/>Divine Law, there needs no Human Diſpenſation, and the exacting of Money in ſuch caſe is unrighteous Gain. The principal Work of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and the ſubſtance of ſo much Church-order and Diſcipline, as is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent on them as Miniſters, to perform and ſee to, conſiſts in labouring in the Word and Doctrine, in preaching the Goſpel, in giving heed to Doctrine, to Exhortation, to Reproof, to Admonition and Inſtruction, publickly, privately, in ſeaſon, out of ſeaſon. Where this is not, the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the Miniſterial Work and Diſcipline is wanting: Where this is all, the reſt will eaſily follow, ſo much as is neceſſary, and what is not neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is better forborn.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The Church is no Church of God, unleſs ſhe have juſt reſpect to time and place for publick Worſhip: and ſhe is equally no Church before God, if ſhe prefer time and place, and bare aſſembling for publick Worſhip, before Chriſtian Faith, Hope, and Love, and Edification therein. As the Sabbath, ſo Time and Place were made for Man, and not Man for them. And therefore the Church is to meet in one, two, or three, or more places at the ſame time, according as it ſhall be for Edification. And look as it is a good Argument for Infant Baptiſm, the Primitive Patern is baptizing whole Houſholds; and therefore in baptizing Infants we keep to the Primitive Patern, Infants being a neceſſary part of Houſholds. So I ſhould think it a good Argument againſt the Congregationaliſts: The Primitive Patern was, that all the Chriſtians in a City be one Church particular; and therefore, if now every Chriſtian City be one particular Church, tho the Chriſtians in it are ſo many as to make a hundred, or two hundred Congregations at the fame time, the Primitive Patern is kept; <hi>Act.</hi> 14.23. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.5. It is not the place which make, the Church, but the Church makes the place. Every Chriſtian Nation as ſuch, is a Church governed inviſibly by God through Chriſtian Faith, according to the Scripture: and governed viſibly by the Prince as ſole Supream under God, over all in his Dominions by the Sword. Tho God do make uſe of Paſtors and Miniſters in the guiding and govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his Church, yet he himſelf is ſole Lord over the Couſcience, and only his Voice is to be heard in the Church, and Paſtors and Miniſters have no Authority but what is Temporal, and yet it differs in kind from the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Prince and Magiſtrate. The Church Militant conſiſts of Mortal Men, and Mortal Men can have no Authority Immortal and Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. Paſtors die no leſs than Princes.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="18" type="chapter">
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:175184:22"/>
            <head>CHAP. XVIII. <hi>Of Death, Judgment, Heaven, and Hell everlaſtingly.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. IF Sin had not been, Death had not been; and yet Death unto Elect Men through Faith in Chriſt, is rather Life than Death, as being through God's Grace, the way and paſſage to Life Everlaſting. They die who die eternally: But they, who by Death paſs into eternal Joy immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately in reſpect of their Souls, and whoſe Bodies reſt, and as it were ſleep in the Grave till the Morning of the Reſurrection, and then ſhall awake, and be raiſed glorious, immortal, ſpiritual, like the glorious Body of Chriſt, may be ſaid rather to live than die.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Reſurrection of the wicked is truly from the Merit and purchaſe of Chriſt, and ſpecially the Reſurrection of the Juſt. The Reſurrection, as in it ſelf, is a Priviledg and Bleſſing: That it proves otherwiſe to the Wicked, is from themſelves, not from Chriſt. <hi>As in Adam all die, ſo in Chriſt ſhall all be made alive,</hi> 1 Cor. 15.22.</p>
            <p n="3">3. As Heaven is it into which Chriſt aſcended when he left this World, ſo it is a proper place created and made by God, diſtinct from Earth and Hell. As Heaven means the Saints everlaſting Reſt, prepared for them from before the Foundation of the World, ſo it is not a place but a ſtate of Felicity and Joy above both Time and Place, and all that Man's Heart can now conceive, yet not repugnant and contrary to Time and Place: For it is God himſelf as enjoyed in eternal Bleſſedneſs. Hence it follows, that the Spuls of the Godly by Death, do all of them paſs into eternal Happineſs imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately: For eternal Happineſs not being a place but a ſtate, and the Godly by Death paſſing into Eternity, there can be no imaginable inſtant in which they are not with God in eternal Felicity. Only they do innocent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly long for the Reſurrection, and rejoyce in the ſure hope thereof: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.9, 10.11. With reſpect to the Eye of Senſe outwardly, the Triumphant State of Chriſt began not till he roſe from the Dead, and it was compleat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by his Aſcenſion, and fitting at the Right-hand of God in Glory. With reſpect to the Eye of Faith inwardly, his Triumphant State began immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately after his Death; and while his Body hung dead upon the Croſs, his Soul was with God in Triumphant Joy. In Memory of Chriſt's Reſurrection we rightly obſerve the Lord's-Day, as a Day appointed by God for ſolemn Religious Worſhip, both publickly and privately. The fourth Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, conſidered as repugnant to Life eternal by Faith in Chriſt, is meer Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daical Righteouſneſs, damnable Impiety, and no Command of God: But conſidered as ſubſervient to Life eternal by Faith in Chriſt, ſo it was typical
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:175184:22"/>of Chriſt's Reſt in the Grave, and as typical by his Reſurrection it was to ceaſe and have an end, and in the room of it comes the Lord's Day, as the joyful Day on which our Lord roſe from the Dead, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>th begotten us unto a lively Hope; 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.3, 4. Thus the fourth Commandment, by Faith in Chriſt, is not aboliſhed, but eſtabliſhed; <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.31.</p>
            <p n="4">4. At the Day of Judgment there ſhall be a perfect opening of all the Good that was in the Wicked, and of all the Sin that was in the Righteous: not for the Shame and Terrour of the Righteous, nor for the Honour and Comfort of the Wicked; but that all may have according to their Deeds, and it may appear to all, that God did not like and approve Sin in his own, and that he did not condemn and drinke what was good and commendable in the Wicked; that ſo the Righteous may for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> rejoice in God's Praiſes, and the Mouths of the Wicked may for ever <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. This perfect o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening ſhall be by Conſcience, as God's <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, in each ones Boſom.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Eternal Felicity, conſidered as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of no Degrees: Thus all, both Saints and Angels in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, and all in Hell, be equally miſerable. For greater <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n Eternal, there can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not poſſibly be. Eternal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, admitteth of Degrees: For God, as he is the Righteous <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the World, cannot but by Conſcience, as his Agent in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and Men, eternally difference, as between the Righteous and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, and between the more Wicked and the leſs Wicked, ſo alſo between the more and the leſs abundant in the Love and Service of God, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> according to their Deeds. Thus the Manhood of Chriſt hath a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of Glory than the Angels, and the Angels, who never linned, than the Saints, and eminent Saints, ſuch as Prophets, Apoſtles, and Martyrs, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n ordinary and common Saints. Thus there is perfect Unity, and perfect Diverſity, ſweeteſt Harmony and ſweeteſt Variety, no one hath cauſe to complain, no one hath cauſe to boaſt, he that hath leaſt hath no lack, and he that hath moſt hath nothing over. God is All in All, and Eternity is All in All. Set aſide Eternity, and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Hell, Holineſs and Sin, Angels and Men are meer Dreams and Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. God may do with his own what be pleaſes, but he cannot deny him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and overthrow his own Name, Kingdom, and Glory. And therefore he can in no inſtant annihilate or eternally torment a holy Man: For ſo to do is not Power but Impotency, not Dominion, but Tyranny, and the abuſe of it. God's Dominion is by his Will, and not againſt it; his Will is eſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, and yet freely holy, juſt, and good. But it is repugnant to infinite Holineſs, Juſtice and Goodneſs, to annihilate, or eternally to to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ent a Holy Man.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="19" type="chapter">
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:175184:23"/>
            <head>CHAP. XIX. <hi>Of the Way of Peace.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. TWo Things, as I conceive, do greatly conduce to Unity and Peace among Chriſtians touching Religion: A clear explication of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel-Truth, and forbearing one another in Love. The former I have endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured in the foregoing Chapters; and among Perſons truly conſciencious, a clear explication of the Truth, is in effect the whole Cure. The latter it is not in my Power to procure. Yet this one thing well weighed may do much towards it; that Perſons eminently Godly, may ignorantly hold an Opinion, in it ſelf heretical, and againſt the Foundation of Faith, and yet not hold it heretically, and ſo as do the Ungodly. The reaſon is, becauſe Heavenly and Fundamental Truth, is not by way of Syllogiſm, and Human Argumentation, Major, Minor, and Concluſion, common to us and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, but by way of Holy Likeneſs to God, through Chriſtian Faith, which Heathens have not. He then who holds one Divine Truth with Holy Belief, is thereby free, not from all Errour, but from all reigning Errour. No Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour is ſafe, and yet no meer Man, ſince the Fall of <hi>Adam,</hi> is wholly free from all Errour, and every Godly Man is in a ſafe State, not becauſe of his Errour, but becauſe Heavenly Truth, and not Errour, reigns in him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Apoſtles for ſome time were in an Errour touching the Nature of Chriſt's Kingdom; which Errour, as in it ſelf conſidered, did by conſequence overthrow the Kingdom of Chriſt, and yet, as it was in them, it was no reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Errour. <hi>Acts</hi> 1.6. The Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> was in an Errour, touching the difference between <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentile,</hi> which Errour, conſidered nakedly, as in it ſelf was deſtructive of true Godlineſs, becauſe it did by conſequence in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer God to be partial, unrighteous, and a reſpecter of Perſons: And yet <hi>Peter</hi> in this inſtant was eminently godly. <hi>Act.</hi> 10.34, 35. There is no ſuch thing in God, as Major and Minor, Premiſes and Concluſion, Antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and Conſequent; becauſe all in God is God: And therefore there can be no ſuch thing in the Image of God: For as all in God, is God, ſo all in the Image of God, is the Image of God. Therefore no Man is to be coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted an Heretick, and damnably Erroneous, barely becauſe he holds an Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in it ſelf Heretical, and by Conſequence againſt the Foundation of Faith, all the while he doth ſincerely hate and deteſt and diſown the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecouence of his Errour, not diſcerning that it is juſtly deducible from it. There is great difference between ignorantly holding an Errour, and bowing to an Idol, or worſhipping a falſe God.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If Chriſtian Princes, and Supream Civil Rulers, in their ſeveral Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:175184:23"/>would according to their Duty, and as becomes nurſing Fathers to the Church, ſee with their own Eyes, and upon hearing the Arguments and Allegations on both ſides, wiſely and impartially diſcern, between what is plainly contained in God's Word, and what is not, but is only School-So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſtry, and vain Philoſophy, corrupting Men's Minds from the ſimplicity that is in Chriſt, and ſerving only to create Strife, and to make plain things obſcure; and would enjoin all ſides to inſiſt upon, and unite in plain and wholſome Truth, evident by its own intrinſick Light, to the Conſcience of each Godly Man, through Faith, and either to cut off and forbear all further Diſputes, or manage them in Love, and in the Spirit of Meekneſs, we ſhould ſoon ſee an End of Controverſies concerning Religion. In the mean time it concerns us all to get and keep well grounded Certainty through Faith of our own Salvation, and earneſtly to contend for this Faith. This Certainty is by way of ſpecial Revelation: For all Divine Revelation, ſince <hi>Adam</hi>'s Fall, is either Principal and Special, or Subſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vient and Common. Special and Principal is that, by Faith, in the Hearts of all the Regenerate in various Degrees, and there is no other Special and Principal Divine Revelation ſince <hi>Adam</hi>'s Fall. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.17. and 4.5. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.13. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.1.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Fundamental Truth is not by way of Number, but by way of holy Likeneſs to God, who is ſimply one, and ſimply one is above Number, and not reducible to it. The Father, the Son, and the Holy Ghoſt are three, truly divers and diſtinct, yet not three by way of Number, Order, and Dependence, common to us and Heathens, but by way of unſearchable Diverſity, not to be underſtood ſavingly without Chriſtian Faith<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> which Heathens have not. They who hold, that the Holy Ghoſt proceedeth from the Father, and the Son, do not mean that he proceedeth from them, as from two Firſts: for there cannot poſſibly be two Firſts in God; <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.13. And they who hold, that he proceedeth only from the Father, do yet hold, that he is by Nature very and eternal God, and the Spirit of the Son, and that the Son doth from the Father ſend the Holy Ghoſt the Comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. This ſuppoſed, the Difference ſeems to be but in Word, and not in Subſtance of Matter.</p>
            <p n="5">5. It is evident from <hi>Job</hi> 13.7. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.1, 2, 3. and from the Nature of the thing, that there is the Perſon of God. For God is an intelligent Being, though infinitely intelligent and increated, and every intelligent Being muſt needs be a Perſon; <hi>Gen.</hi> 14.21. <hi>Jon.</hi> 4.11. <hi>Numb.</hi> 31.28. Now they who hold, that the Father, the Son, and the Holy Ghoſt are three diſtinct Perſons, do yet hold that they are but one God. And if they who hold that as they are but one God, ſo they are but one Perſon, do yet hold that the Perſon of God the Father, unbegotten and not incarnate, as
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:175184:24"/>ſuch, is not the Perſon of God the Son, begotten and incarnate, in my opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion they both hold the ſame fundamental and neceſſary Truth, and do but differ in Word. The common School-Doctrine, that in the Trinity there is <hi>alius &amp; alius,</hi> but not <hi>aliud &amp; aliud:</hi> And in Chriſt <hi>aliud &amp; aliud,</hi> but not <hi>alius &amp; alius,</hi> I conceive to be an Errour. For <hi>aliud &amp; aliud</hi> muſt needs mean either Contrariety or Diverſity: If it mean Contrariety, then it is falſe that there is Contrariety in Chriſt: If it mean Diverſity, then it is falſe, that there is not Diverſicy in the Trinity. So the common diſtinction of the Works of God within God, and without God, <hi>ad intra &amp; adextra,</hi> is certainly an Errour. For every Work of God is an effect ſimply dependent upon his free Pleaſure; <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.11. But no dependence can be in God, all in God is ſimply independent. And as there cannot be a Creature without a Creator, ſo there cannot poſſibly be a Work of God without God; <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.3. And look as it is ſaid, of his own Will God begat us, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.18. So equally it may be ſaid, of his own Will he made all Things, and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not of Nothing: For God's Will is not nothing, but it is the prime Cauſe, and the prime Cauſe is ſuperlatively material to our Faith.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="20" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. XX. <hi>Of Sin, and particularly of the Sin againſt the Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. SIN is the Tranſgreſſion of the Law, the Wages whereof according to legal Juſtice, is eternal Damnation: or, it is the Undoing of Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and Soul for ever in Hell, if God's Grace in Chriſt prevent not by giving Repentance and Pardon. Look as all in God, is God, ſo all in Sin, is Sin. With reſpect to human Judicature, Sin is an Effect, and Man's Will is the true Cauſe of it: With reſpect to Divine Judicature it is no Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, and therefore it can have no Cauſe, but all that ſin tranſgreſs without Cauſe. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.3. <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.25. As to human Judicature, Sin is an Accident, a thing that comes to paſs in time, and is diſtinct from Man's natural Subſtance, and is truly evitable: As to Divine Judicature, it is no Accident: For from Eternity it was future, it hath Dominion over the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly, and as never repented of, it abides in the Conſcience for ever, and breeds the never-dying Worm. This cannot be affirmed of an Accident, <hi>quod ſubjecto ineſt, &amp; quod poteſt adeſſe, vel abeſſe abſque ſubjecti Interitu:</hi> For nothing eternal, can be accidental. It is one and the ſame thing, which is both Sin and Guilt, but not in the ſame reſpects. Sin as pleaſant, ungodly Men do naturally love: but as Gu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lt doth intrinſecally go along, with Sin, and gripe their Conſcience, and fill them with legal Terrour, ſo they do naturally hate and flee from it. They love Sin, but not Hell.</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:175184:24"/>
            <p n="2">2. The Holy Ghoſt in Scripture is taken two ways, either for God the Holy Ghoſt, and ſo we are baptized in his Name: Or for an Effect pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced by him. Hereof there are two Kinds, principal and ſubſervient: principal is that Divine and Holy Nature, which God doth plant in the Hearts of all the Regenerate, in the inſtant of their Pardon and Juſtification by Faith. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.13, 14. The Holy Ghoſt in this Senſe, none of thoſe, now in Hell did at any time partake of. Conſidered, as a ſubſervient Effect, ſo it was eminently poured forth on the Apoſtles upon the day of Pentecoſt, and was common in that firſt Age of the Chriſtian Church: It conſiſted in the Gift of Tongues, of Healing, of caſting out of Devils, and other mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous Diſtributions. The Holy Ghoſt in this Senſe, many never Regenerate might partake of, and afterward totally fall away &amp; periſh eternally. And this, for ought I know, is the meaning of the Holy Ghoſt, in that much contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted Scripture, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.4, 5, 6. compared with <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.22, 23. and 12.24, to 32. <hi>Act.</hi> 2. and 8.17. and 10.44, 45, 46. and 19. 2, 3, 4, 5, 6. <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.20. <hi>Joh.</hi> 7.39.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Sin againſt the Holy Ghoſt is therefore ſimply unpardonable, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Perſon guilty of it is juſtly forſaken of God, given up to a repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate Senſe, to final Obduration in Sin, and to ſtrong Deluſion to believe a Lie, and ſo he cannot but be finally impenitent, and incurably graceleſs. It ſeems to be a Degree of that kind of implacable Enmity againſt God, and his holy Image, which is in the Devil himſelf. The Devils believe and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: they cannot but have an inward Senſe and Conviction, that Jeſus Chriſt is the Saviour of the World, and the Judg of all, both quick and dead, and that the Religion contained in the Bible, and ſincerely profeſſed by <hi>Abel, Moſes, Peter, Paul,</hi> and the reſt of the Elect, in all Ages, is the only true Religion. And yet being eternally forſaken of God, and left to themſelves, they have no power evangelically to repent, they cannot but im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placably hate God, and his holy Image, blaſpheme his Truth and pure Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and endeavour the utter Extinction of it, and the eternal Ruin of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Man.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>I was before a Blaſphemer, and a Perſocuter, and Injurious. But I obtained Mercy; becauſe I did it ignorantly, in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelief.</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.13. This implies that had he done it wilfully, and knowingly, againſt the inward Belief and Conviction of his Conſcience, his Caſe had been very perilous. In my Opinion, the ſafeſt and eaſieſt way to underſtand what is the Sin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Holy Ghoſt, is to make the Devil himſelf the Standard of it. Though all ungodly Perſons be the Children of the Devil, yet as they are not all Atheiſts, Murderers, Adulterers, Sodomites, Perjured, Traitors; ſo they are not all guilty of the Sin againſt the Holy Ghoſt. They who make Conſcience of their ways, and fear to ſin againſt God, may be ſure
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:175184:25"/>they have not committed this unpardonable Sin. They who have been convinced and perſwaded of God's true Religion, and have ſolemnly covenanted and engaged their Souls to God, in Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, and have profeſſed the way of Truth, if afterward they ſhall renounce the true Religion, and blaſpheme it, and perſecute the ſincere Profeſſour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of it, and ſhall ſuffer themſelves to be deluded, ſo as to believe Lies contrary to the true Religion, I think the Caſe of ſuch is very perilous.</p>
            <p n="5">5. We are to pray for all Men now living, and that ſhall live hereafter, but not for thoſe whom we know to have committed the Sin againſt the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.16. For the Rule of Prayer is not God's unſearcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Preſcience, what will be, but God's Law obliging us to love our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour as our ſelves, and in Token thereof to pray for him, while there is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Hope. Now of all Ungodly Men, while in the World, there is huma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Hope, which is a kind of middle State between the Godly, in whom is Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Hope of Salvation, and the Damned in Hell, and Perſons guilty of the Sin againſt the Holy Ghoſt, of whom there can be no Hope at all. As for ſuch as teach that we muſt pray for all ſorts of Men, but not for all of every ſort, <hi>pro generibus ſingulorum, ſed non pro ſingulis generûm,</hi> it ſeems to be vain deceit. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.8. For bare Generals, as diſtinct from all the Indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duals and Particulars, is a meer Chimera. Chriſt, as Man, prayed for all and in this he is our Patern. Chriſt, as God the Son incarnate, did not pray for all, but did omnipotently intercede for thoſe only whoſe Salvation was future, and for none elſe, ſo as for them. In this he is not our Patern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>but infinitely above us. <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.9, 20. <hi>Luk.</hi> 23.34.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Pag. 6. line 39. read <hi>Counterprice.</hi> P. 22. l. 27. r. <hi>Exigencies.</hi> P. 25. l. 21. r. <hi>theſe</hi> P. 27. l. 39. f. <hi>Decree,</hi> r. <hi>Graece.</hi> P. 28. l. 8. r. <hi>to.</hi> P. 29. l. 2. r. <hi>indelibly.</hi> P. 32. l. 2, 1. <hi>Index.</hi> P. 34. l. 17. r. <hi>principal and.</hi> P. 37. l. 26. r. <hi>which makes.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
